<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A clear apology and just defence of Richard Stafford for himself with a rehearsal, and further explanation of what he hath done concerning national affairs.</title>
            <author>Stafford, Richard, 1663-1703.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1690</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 137 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A61217</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S5110</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R219673</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99831127</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99831127</idno>
            <idno type="VID">35589</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A61217)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 35589)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2113:09)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A clear apology and just defence of Richard Stafford for himself with a rehearsal, and further explanation of what he hath done concerning national affairs.</title>
                  <author>Stafford, Richard, 1663-1703.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 36 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the year 1690.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication suggested by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Copy has print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>James --  II, --  King of England, 1633-1701 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:35589:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>A Clear APOLOGY AND Juſt Defence OF </hi>
               <hi rend="blackletterType">Richard Stafford</hi>
               <hi> For Himſelf;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>With a Rehearſal, and further Explanation of what he hath done concerning National Affairs.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>But truly, I am full of Power by the Spirit of the Lord, and of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and of Might, to declare unto <hi>Jacob</hi> his Tranſgreſſion, and to <hi>Iſrael</hi> his Sin. Hear this, I pray you, ye Heads of the Houſe of <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob,</hi> and Princes of the Houſe of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> that abhor Judgment, and pervert all Equity: They build up <hi>Zion</hi> with Blood, and <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> with Iniquity: The Heads thereof judge for Reward, and the Prieſts there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of teach for Hire, and the Prophets thereof divine for Money; yet will they lean upon the Lord, and ſay, Is not the Lord among us? none evil can come upon us, <bibl>
                  <hi>Micah</hi> 3. 8, 9, 10, 11.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>But Judgment ſhall return unto Righteouſneſs, and all the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pright in heart ſhall follow it, <bibl>
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 94. 15.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>All the Words of my Mouth are in Righteouſneſs, there is nothing fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward or perverſe in them: They are all plain to him that underſtandeth, and right to them that find Knowledge, <bibl>
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 8. 8, 9.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Printed in the Year</hi> 1690.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:35589:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:35589:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi> Preface may ſeem unuſual and impertinent before an Apology; But it is neceſſary to advertiſe the Reader ſomewhat before, leſt, when he comes to ſee ſuch ſerious Truth applied ſo exceeding cloſe and force<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably, He be frightened quite away, that he cannot endure to ſee what here is Publiſhed. And there will ariſe a ſecret Prejudice why I ſhould not ſeek out <hi>ſmooth Things</hi> and Soft Words as do others; but <hi>the Land is not able to bear all theſe Words.</hi> Why then doth the <hi>Land</hi> act and commit ſuch Things, which are here ſpoken of with more Peace and Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs than they are done? Indeed I am naturally averſe from tormenting the Minds of Men; and alſo I do underſtand what becomes Education, Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vility and Cuſtom of the world, as do others. But it being my Duty and Buſineſs (according to the Grace and Knowledge intruſted with me) to endeavour to turn People from Iniquity unto Righteouſneſs, I ought (or otherwiſe I am not faithful in my Office) to uſe the moſt cogent Arguments, and to preſs them with the utmoſt force and power which I can. <hi>The Words of the Wiſe are like Nails faſtened by the Maſter of Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies;</hi> ſo whoever doth not drive the Nail of Exhortation home to the very head, and faſten it as much as he can on every ſide, He doth the <hi>Work of the Lord deceitfully.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is groſs Ignorance and fooliſh Imagination to be frightened at <hi>Words;</hi> for they do expreſs <hi>Things</hi> which have been, or are now tranſacting and paſſing on, or ſhall be hereafter; and theſe (not the bare Picture and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Repreſentation of them) we ſhould indeed fear and endeaevour to avoid. VVe think it better and more ſafe to read of a pitcht Battel, a bloody Sea-fight, a conſuming Fire, Plague, or ſuch like, than to be in the midſt thereof; yea, We would willingly know thereof, and be ſhewed the way how we may keep out, eſcape and prevent ſuch evil things: So likewiſe, every one doth deſire to hear and know of Good Things, and how themſelves may obtain and partake thereof. It is the ſame, yea, more Danger and Loſs to be <hi>willingly Ignorant</hi> of what is contained in the Word of God. For as ſure as things were firſt made, are now upheld, have their beginning and end, increaſe and decreaſe, and every Thing is according to its Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb facs="tcp:35589:3"/> and Kind, and moves and goes on, as we now ſee with our bodily Eyes, we look upon, and our Hands handle, and we conceive in our minds; ſo the <hi>ſame Word</hi> will be to every tittle fulfilled, as we are warned and foretold of. <hi>But the Heavens and the Earth, which are now, by the ſame Word are kept in ſtore, reſerved unto Fire againſt the Day of Judgment, and Perdition of Ungodly Men,</hi> 2 Pet. 3. 7. It is the worſt ſort of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ngodlineſs, not to like to <hi>receive God into their know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge.</hi> It is <hi>Rebellion which is as the Sin of Witchcraft, and Stub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bornneſs which is as Iniquity and Idolatry to reject the Word of the Lord,</hi> 1 Sam. 15. 23. as was ſaid to <hi>Saul</hi> the King; for even the Kings and Judges of the Earth do commit Rebellion againſt God.</p>
            <p>We will here aſſert the Government of God over all Nations and Rulers, come what will of it to my weak and frail Perſon; as themſelves muſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge, &amp; cannot gain-ſay the ſame. Nor yet do they well to be angry with one who is <hi>a Worm, and no man; a Reproach of men, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed of the People:</hi> for as they are Reaſonable Creatures, Themſelves would not have <hi>deſtruction come upon them at unawares;</hi> and not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the ſecret excuſe they have now, every man in the deep of his Heart, yet then they will think it hard (but juſt) to be condemned for what they knew not, but might have known if they would. If they will <hi>Still Deſpiſe, and Wonder and Periſh,</hi> it is to themſelves. If they think ſuch an one is mad, only becauſe he would prevent their own Miſery, then indeed <hi>their Eyes are darkened that they ſee not.</hi> It happens here according to Chriſt's Method and Prediction, <hi>that they which ſee not, might ſee; and they which ſee, might be made Blind,</hi> John 9. 39. Poor and Ignorant People do diſcern the Truth, when it is hidden from the Wiſe and Prudent whom it moſt concerns. <hi>In the latter dayes they ſhall conſider it perfectly,</hi> VVhen for Deſpiſing will be Anguiſh and ſad Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flection; for Stubbornneſs, Pain and Miſery.</p>
            <p>VVhatever kind of reception theſe VVords ſhall meet with in the world, The beſt <hi>Apology</hi> for them is their own <hi>Truth and Signification.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:35589:3"/>
            <head>A Clear APOLOGY and Juſt Defence of <hi>Richard Stafford</hi> for himſelf, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THe Word <hi>Apology</hi> in common apprehenſion, ſeems to preſuppoſe fault or inferiority; and doth often come by way of Excuſe, mitigation or beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging Pardon. Whereas the Compiler of theſe following Lines, is not conſcious to himſelf of any Crime or Offence he hath done to his own Nation. And alſo as he ſtands in the rank of Creatures, h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> will not acknowledge ſo much of the other, as the <hi>Pride of Man,</hi> and <hi>Arrogancy of Tongues</hi> would ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine and ſpeak forth.</p>
            <p>But to get out from the Perplexity and Labyrinth of <hi>Words</hi> and <hi>Perſons,</hi> come we to <hi>Things;</hi> and we would no otherwiſe conſider the ſeveral Thoughts, Words and Actions of mankind, but with relation to them. Indeed we cannot know as God knows; for that we may take the more notice of it, it is thrice aſſerted and repeat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>The Lord looketh from Heaven; He beholdeth all the Sons of Men, from the place of his Habitation he looketh upon all the Inhabitants of the Earth, He faſhioneth their Hearts alike: He conſidereth all their Works</hi> Pſal. 33. 13, 14, 15. whether Good or Evil, to Reward or Puniſh: <hi>And give to every Man according to his Ways, whoſe Heart thou knoweſt; for thou, even thou only knoweſt the Hearts of all the Children of Men,</hi> 1 Kings 8. 39. This is the alone <hi>Prerogative</hi> of God; for He knoweth all things, and ſearcheth the Heart, that not the leaſt Thing can be hid or concealed from him. Whereas we only perceive a little according to the exact Truth; but much more in a falſe and imperfect manner by doubtful Report and miſtaken Obſervation. And then we cannot throughly apprehend a thing wherein many are concerned; ſo we can give no perfect Judgment and Determination.</p>
            <p>God hath taken the like method for the exerciſe and adminiſtration of his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and Dominion over Men; as our Kings and Governours over their ſeveral Countries. And he hath a Book for his Government over all the Nations and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies of the Earth (high and low, rich and poor together) as our Statute and Common Law is for <hi>England;</hi> and their civil, canon or municipal Laws for other Nations. His Word is given unto Mankind to be a Rule for their Actions, and a Law for them to live and be governed by: and from that we are allowed and commanded to <hi>Reprove</hi> all manner of Sin and Tranſgreſſion; as any one now doth <note place="margin">Lev. 19. 17.</note> take notice or ſpeak of what is done contrary to the Government and Laws of this Nation; which is eſteemed no fault, but rather commendable, and a Duty. The ſame is, and ought much more to be in things pertaining to God; and ſo likewiſe would be, if there was amongſt us the like Zeal for and Knowledge of him that is inviſible, who fills Heaven and Earth with his Preſence; as now there is regard for the Son of Man, whom we ſee to be little, and to <hi>fade as a Leaf.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But this is to be underſtood for the Fear and Inſtruction of ſome, and for the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of others; That God is not confined to the Imaginations and Sayings of Men: If ſome ſpeak <hi>ſmooth things</hi> and <hi>propheſie Deceits;</hi> and others too hard Speeches and miſtaken Applications; The <hi>Judge himſelf</hi> will not ratifie what they ſay, but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demns
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:35589:4"/> whom man abſolves, as again acquit whom man condemns. <hi>For he cometh, for he cometh to judge the Earth: He ſhall judge the World with Righteouſneſs, and the People with his Truth,</hi> Pſal. 96. 13. <hi>And I ſaw the dead, ſmall and great, ſtand before God; and the Books were opened, and another Book was opened, which is the Book of Life: and the dead were judged out of thoſe Things, which were written in the Books according to their Works,</hi> Rev. 20. 12. This, according to the Decree of the Eternal and unchange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able God, is as certain and True, as if it were already paſt and fulfilled. As Judges and Juſtices of <hi>Gaol delivery</hi> do try Priſoners by the ſtatute Book of this Realm at thoſe <hi>Aſſizes</hi> which are holden twice a year, ſo at this general <hi>Grave delivery</hi> which is to be kept once for all, The dead Bodies of all People, of every Place and Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration ſince Man was Created on the Earth, ſhall ariſe, and we ſhall all be judged by Chriſt and his Saints according to thoſe Words written in the Bible: And this accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the plain and common ſence and underſtanding of the ſame Words.</p>
            <p>Behold in this they are not juſt, I will anſwer all mine Accuſers and Enemies that <hi>God is greater than Man;</hi> and ſo much do his Laws exceed theirs. Wherefore do I mention that God is greater than Man? In compariſon of him the <hi>Nations are as a drop of a Bucker, and are counted as the ſmall duſt of the Balance. It is He that ſitteth up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the circle of the Earth, and the Inhabitants thereof are as Graſhoppers.</hi> We ſhall find and know that <hi>He bringeth the Princes to nothing; He maketh the Judges of the Earth as <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>anity.</hi> Notwithſtanding the People have more regard to them becauſe they are ſeen and their utmoſt Power is known; then they have to Almighty God, who is not ſeen, and whoſe Puniſhment is threatned. But though God is not ſeen, yet his Works are. And how Great muſt He be who built this vaſt Houſe of the World, and cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated all things therein? What is the <hi>Wrath</hi> of a Worm of five or ſix foot long, to the <note n="*" place="margin">Iſa. 59. 15.</note> 
               <hi>Diſpleaſure</hi> of Him, who hath Heaven for his Throne, and the Earth for his Foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtool? What is a ſingle <hi>Individual</hi> or an Aſſembly of Men, who <hi>dwell in Houſes of Clay</hi> that they ſhould (when met in Council) <hi>as yet exalt themſelves</hi> to do according to their own will, notwithſtanding Gods Commandment to the contrary? If not to ſpeak <note place="margin">Exod 9. 17.</note> out, (becauſe they profeſs that they know God, but in Works deny him) yet to think and act <hi>Marvellous things againſt the God of Gods,</hi> Dan. 11. 36. And in this they are worſe then him here ſpoken of, or <hi>Pharoah,</hi> for he knew not who was the Lord that he ſhould obey him. What is abomination of Heart, they imagine to be bravery of mind; that they can, and are for doing things otherwiſe, and as it were hinder that his will be not done here on Earth. Which argues the exceeding ſinfulneſs of ſin, with the infinite guilt and demerit thereof, and it ſhall be puniſhed with proportionable Condemnation &amp; Miſery. <hi>They are corrupt, and ſpeak wickedly concerning oppreſſion: They ſpeak loftily: They ſet their Mouth againſt the Heavens; &amp; their Tongue walketh through the Earth, therefore his People return hither and Waters of a full Cup are wring out to them.</hi> Pſal. 73. 8, 9, 10. By the height and breadth and depth of ſuch kind of Tranſgreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, we may judge of the length of future Torments. Whoſe Thoughts were thus <hi>exalted to Heaven,</hi> their Souls ſhall be <hi>thruſt down to Hell.</hi> Shall not God ſearch this <note place="margin">Luk. 10. 15.</note> out? for He knoweth the ſecrets of the Heart, the innermoſt Thoughts and moſt hidden Imaginations. Even now he looks down from the Habitation of his Holineſs, and is not far from every one of us; for at this very moment, He both ſees and hears all that we are talking of or doing in our Houſes and ſeveral places of abode. And ſo He hath done all along of this Generation of Men now living, as He did of thoſe before we were born. We read of Him in his Word, <hi>for the Lord your God is God of Gods, and Lord of Lords, a great God, a Mighty and a Terrible, which regardeth not</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:35589:4" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
               <hi>Perſons nor taketh Reward.</hi> Deut. 10. 17. We have a ſence, and aw, and dread of Him upon our minds; we may know and perceive his Laws written in our Hearts and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Parts; by laying open our Conſcience as in his ſight, and by communing with our own ſpirit, when we are for a little while ſilent in our Chamber, and ſomewhat freed and ſeparated from the: Things of this World. All theſe wayes God doth ſhew and manifeſt himſelf unto Mankind; ſo that they are without excuſe.</p>
            <p>This may be thought proper to inſtruct and convert Heathens, or the neighbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Nations which do grovel in the darkneſs of Popiſh ignorance, but doth not ſeem ſo applicable to our own Countrey, where the Scriptures are read and preached in a known Tongue, and they boaſt of their underſtanding thereof. But yet the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet ſaith peremptorily of his time, when they had the ſame priviledges, <hi>Therefore my P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ople are gone into captivity becauſe they have no knowledge<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> Iſa. 5. 13. He doth elegantly hint of the ſottiſh ignorance of former, his own, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>cceſſive Generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, <hi>Have ye not krown? Have ye not heard? Hath it not been <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> you from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning? Have ye not underſtood from the Foundations of the Earth?</hi> Iſa. 40. 21. And then doth as it were point him out in the following verſe, <hi>It is He</hi> &amp;c. So it is ſaid further down, <hi>There is no knowledge of God in the Land,</hi> Hoſ. 4. 1. And what Paul witneſſeth of his time, <hi>Some have not the knowledge of God, I ſpeak this to your ſhame,</hi> 1 Cor. 15. 34. The ſame is affirmed at this very day, The chief, and who call themſelves the wiſe Men of this Nation, in this they are found wanting. <hi>They have not the knowledge of God.</hi> This is the manner of the People of <hi>England</hi> that dwell careleſly, that ſay in their Hearts, We are and none beſides us. Here is a ſecret diſowning of God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove. Or if they acknowledge him by a few acts of outward Worſhip; yet they confine all to that. But they have not to do with him in common actions, and gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral courſe of their Life. Here they conclude, they are leſt to themſelves, <hi>who is Lord over us?</hi> ſome others will have reſpect unto God in little trivial concerns; But for thoſe of Greater Moment <hi>They do not take counſel of him, that walk to go down into Egypt, and have not asked at my Mouth,</hi> Iſa. 30. 1, 2. They have firſt invaded this Nation, which occaſioned and raiſed Wars in the Neighbouring Kingdoms: But they did not ſeek out of the Book of the Lord, whether ſuch enterpriſes at firſt were juſt and lawful. Why <hi>Ramoth in Gilead</hi> was ours before? 1. Kings 22. 2. and under the ſubjection of the ſame King of this Nation. And though now it be in danger to fall into the hands of the King of <hi>Syria;</hi> yet they ſhould have done well at the very be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of all to have <hi>enquired at the Word of the Lord.</hi> verſe, 5. and then all this might have been prevented at the very firſt riſe. And now the Land is moved and divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and by reaſon of the ſores thereof, it ſhaketh; yet it may be made up and healed by our God. Now <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rim</hi> and <hi>Thummim</hi> are ceaſed; neither have we Warrant for additional Immediate Revelation; But God hath given us his ſtanding Word in the Bible, which was confirmed by Signs and Miracles, and divers Giffts of the Holy Ghoſt: whereby God himſelf did bear witneſs to it, and did enact and confirm it as a Law and Direction to our fore-Fathers, and to us their Children, and to our Poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty for evermore. <hi>He hath ſhewed thee O Man, what is good; and what doth the Lord require of thee, but to do juſtly, and love Mercy?</hi> Mic. 6. 8. By this way and method of Righteous and prudent accomodation <hi>Ireland</hi> might be ſooner recovered and utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſentangled from out of the hands of the <hi>French King,</hi> then by all the Multitude of Men and Horſes, Ships and Carriages, the ſeveral Inſtruments of Death and Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty: all which only make a meer noiſe and outward ſhew, but there is nothing more in it beſides Deſtruction and Miſchief.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:35589:5"/>
            <p> But our Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erno<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ate not Governed by the Law of the moſt High God and ſo they do not <hi>walk Humbly with him;</hi> They do not conſider that in the Thing wherein they deal Proudly, he is above them; they do not conſult aright for his Glory; nor will they obey him ſo far that he may direct their work in Truth. <hi>They have ſet up Kings, but not by me; They have made Princes, but I knew it not,</hi> Hoſ. 8. 4. which hath been particularly ſhewed with ſuch Evidence and Demonſtration of <hi>Divine Truth;</hi> that the ſinners reſort only to their old accuſtomed method of ſtubbornneſs, deſpiſing and bare contradiction; but ſtill it remains firm and unanſwerable. And this hath been already done in two diſtinct Seſſions of Parliament in two ſhort Printed Feſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of Truth; the firſt entituled a Supplemental Tract of Government &amp;c. bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing date <hi>Jan.</hi> 4. 1689, 90. The ſecond, Things Plain and Weighty referred to the conſideration of both Houſes March, 25. 1690. That peace and Happineſs, Truth and Juſtice, Religion and Piety may be eſtabliſhed among us for all Generations.</p>
            <p>For themſelves <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ay in the ſame words in the place where they are aſſembled every morning before their ſolemn conſultations, and therefore it may ſeem ſtrange (unleſs an unſeen Enemy did blind their Eyes and Hearts, or hinder from diſcerning, or turn them aſide from the Truth) that when God hath ſhewed them a way in his Word and left the means in their Power; yet they did not go the right way to preſerve, make better and perpetuate the Government; nor to Reſtore Peace, nor make Wars to ceaſe: all which by the direction of Gods Word will be done, to the end of time, and to the ends of the Earth, <hi>when they ſball fear the Name of the Lord from the Weſt.</hi> Iſa. 59. 19. and other Nations will alſo do the ſame, as they have from this underſtanding People a right example. And fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, there is the Promiſe of God that future Generations ſhall <note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 102. 28. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ct <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>2. 5.</note> 
               <hi>Continue</hi> what we have happily begun. It is only to <hi>order things and to eſtabliſh them with Judgment and with Juſtice, from hence forth even for ever.</hi> To obſerve and do according to thoſe Laws, Rules and Directions which the Lord hath ſhewed and appointed in his Word; and then there would be continued peace and firm ſettlement throughout theſe three Kingdoms, which are united one to another; and the like might be ſucceſſively eſta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>liſhed throughout the whole Earth. <hi>Let us <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>e come, and fix upon the ſure Foundation of Righteouſneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But otherwiſe there will be confuſion, diſturbance and unſetledneſs of Times, with the manifold evils and Inconveniences thereof now in this place, beſides the Wrath of God which hereafter cometh upon the Children of Diſobedience. If People will go on ſtill in their own Wayes and according to their own Thoughts, this is Sin, Iniquity and Tranſgreſſion; all which the Lord God of Recompences ſhall ſurely requite. <hi>None calleth for Juſtice, nor any pleadeth for Truth: they truſt in vanity and ſpeak lies; They conceive miſchief and bring forth iniquity; they hath Cockatrice Eggs, and</hi> 
               <note place="margin">See Iſa. 59. throughout.</note> 
               <hi>weave the Spiders Web. He that eateth of their Eggs dieth; and that which is craſhed breaketh out into a Viper.</hi> What is done by way of Violence, Humour and Stub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>orn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, will recoyl with greater force and ſmart upon themſelves; notwithſtanding they die as other men; and we ſee nothing as yet to befall them. Again, ſometimes it is here ſeen, that what they would ſuppreſs doth riſe up with greater ſtrength and danger againſt them. Or if with much ſubtlety and contrivance, <hi>They weave the Spiders Web; yet theſe VVebs ſhall</hi> not become Garments, neither ſhall <hi>they cover themſelves with their VVorks.</hi> It may juſt skin a thing over; which nevertheleſs will be ſeen through. And it doth not anſwer the ends of Government as to give real peace and aſſured Preſervation. Indeed it is a little better then nothing, for it is
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:35589:5"/> ſomewhat caſt over, which doth neither hide nakedneſs nor keep warm. And then it is a long time in tranſacting and making; but it is all ſuddenly ſwept away, and profits nothing at all afterwards.</p>
            <p>We have an example and inſtance hereof in the late Reign; when the King not obſerving the Rules of <hi>Mercy, Judgment and Righteouſneſs,</hi> was not <hi>Eſtabliſhed in his</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 16. 5.</note> 
               <hi>Throne,</hi> but hath been ſince removed. It is obſervable of thoſe arbitrary and illegal Acts which he did, That he was two or three years in bringing them to paſs; but they were undone again in two or three dayes, or leſs than a week. And he did offer to do all things for the future as became a Good King. God knows the ſecrets and intents of his Heart; and whether it was not more out of apprehenſion of danger than real Repentance; but that might have brought him to a ſight of his Sin and Errour, and then it would have been real and unfeigned: for affliction and fear are ſuch a beginning of Repentance as God will accept of, and therefore we may allow the ſame to one another in things that they have treſpaſſed againſt us. But it was not done according to Righteouſneſs, Equity, Truth or Chriſtian Forgiveneſs. In the great National Revolution was that fulfilled, <hi>They proceed from Evil to Evil, and they know not me, ſaith the Lord,</hi> Jer. 9. 3. One unlawful extream doth not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe and juſtifie another of deſpiſing the Oath of God, breaking his Covenant, and tranſgreſſing the Laws of Righteouſneſs.</p>
            <p>There are many Particulars and Circumſtances of Sin and Evil of both ſides, which no man knoweth nor conſidereth the utmoſt Evil and Abomination of. But the Lord ſhall rehearſe it, when he writeth up his People. He hath a Book of all Nations, Families and ſingle Perſons, with an account of the Time and Place they ſtand here on the Earth. As likewiſe he notes the things that they have already done, &amp; his all-knowing Spirit will bring out the very truth of all things: Though he now keeps ſilence, yet he will reprove the ſeveral Perſons concerned herein, and ſet the things they have done before their Eyes: <hi>For there is no reſpect of Perſons with God; for as many as have ſinned without Law, ſhall alſo periſh without Law, and as many as have ſinned in the Law, ſhall be judged by the Law</hi> Rom, 2. 11, 12. <hi>But he that doth wrong, ſhall receive for the wrong which he hath done, and there is no reſpect of Perſons,</hi> Col. 3. 25.</p>
            <p>But alledge as much as you will of this, it is Scripture and Cant, and is not minded; ſo may a common Thief or Murderer, or any Tranſgreſſor of man's Laws, for a time deſpiſe, and not regard them: yet Juſtice will at length apprehend and <note place="margin">Zech. 1. 6.</note> overcome him. In like manner, the Words and Statutes of the Lord will <hi>take hold</hi> of men of every Generation and Country; and as to each part of their Life after they are come to the knowledge of good and evil. Some do imagine that they ſhall eſcape, becauſe they have the chief of the People, and the Multitude, and the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion and the <hi>Courſe of the World</hi> on their ſide. They have Armies and Fleetes; and ſuch an one is driven away and oppreſſed, and of declining Years. He may be taken captive or Killed, or his day come to dye. What then? We have to do with an Almighty and Everliving God. Our ſelves and all the many Inhabitants of the Earth, are but a <hi>parcel of dying Men and Women,</hi> and ſo take them altogether, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding their number, they are all <hi>contemptible and of ſmall Power.</hi> And thoſe who in this time of Tryal will <hi>follow a Multitude to do Evil,</hi> or ſide with the <hi>courſe of the World</hi> in their Tranſgreſſion and Unrighteouſneſs; As ſure as God hath given a Law to mankind, and his Word is true, this is the ready way to be <hi>condemned with the World,</hi> Let men in the mean while make what alterations they will, all is but as a company of Worms of the Earth, who vainly think to change Times,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:35589:6"/> Laws and Ordinances; But they are all juſt like ſo many Ants, which are a long time bringing little Sticks and Straws together; which is all ſuddenly blown away with one ſingle blaſt of Wind; much leſs will it ſtand until; or at that day when <hi>our God ſhall come, and it ſhall be very tempeſtuous round about him,</hi> Pſal. 50. 3. There can be no ſuch thing as a Law, unleſs it be ſounded on Divine Right and Eternal Truth.</p>
            <p>And therefore it was a fooliſh and wicked Imagination of ſuch who know not God, and did conclude it impertinent to bring Scripture to manifeſt that in the late Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volution of putting down one King, and ſetting up another, the Nation of <hi>England</hi> hath not done Righteouſneſs; for how could this be known otherwiſe than by Scripture, the higheſt Law, which God himſelf hath given to mankind of every Nation, Country and Language, Every thing is to be tryed and judged by this ſupream Rule of good and evil, truth and falſhood, right and wrong. We are to be accountable to God for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll our Actions, and muſt receive according to what we have done. It is God who eſtabliſheth Kingdoms and Property; and his Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion over us is above all man's Government; for this is inferior, and ought only to be in ſubordination under God; from whom men receive authority to make National Laws, and to exerciſe their own Rule and Dominion: The great Law-giver hath kept this in his own Power; for his Word and Commandment is left for Admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Reproof, that the Kings and Judges of the Earth do only that which is juſt and lawful; but if they do not, they are warned to amend, otherwiſe they will be condemned.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>God ſtandeth in the Congregation of the mighty; he judgeth among the Gods,</hi> Pſal. 82. 1. There is an aſſertion of his own Government over all Kings and Magiſtrates, unto whom he vouchſafes to give his own Name. And then comes in afterwards by way of Reproof, <hi>How long will ye judge unjuſtly, and accept the Perſons of the Wicked, ſelap,</hi> Verſ. 2. Then ſucceeds his Command, <hi>Defend the Poor and Father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, To Juſtice to the Afflicted and Needy: Deliver the Poor and Needy; rid them out of the Hand of the Wicked,</hi> Verſ. 3. 4. And as all Scripture is profitable for Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, for Inſtruction in Righteouſneſs, ſo in order to that, it doth take notice of what is amiſs, <hi>they know not neither will They underſtand, they walk <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> darkneſs, all the Foundations of the Earth are out of courſe,</hi> verſ. 5. and throughout Gods Word and Law there are directions and commands to ſet them in right order again. But that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains in a dead letter, and it is not faithfully handled nor univerſally applyed; for <hi>the Prieſts have been partial in the Law.</hi> They have kept back ſome part of it, and have not made known the whole counſel of God unto the People: And alſo accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the marginal reading of <hi>Mal.</hi> 2. 9. They have <hi>accepted Faces,</hi> by applying it ſuperficially and favourably to the higher ſort of People. As they have done and do not ceaſe to <hi>juſtifie the Wicked for Reward,</hi> for ſome Place or preferment either already beſtowed, or in hope and expectation to be given, And ſo it comes to paſs that Gods faithful Meſſengers (who have appeared in their ſeveral Generations as ſingular) are perſecuted and proſecuted. Now God doth lie ſtill and hide himſelf to ſee what the Children of Men will do. Though it is the ſecret continued Prayer of his Elect and Servants, <hi>Ariſe O God, Judge the Earth; for thou ſhalt inherit all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> Pſal. 82. 8. Yet He will not before the appointed time. But his Law is given in the mean while, and he doth prove the doings of the Children of Men.</p>
            <p>There hath been a long and continued controverſie in the World throughout for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Generations, and in all Nations; and the ſame continues at this day, not only
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:35589:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> amongſt <hi>Heathens, Mahometans, Papiſts,</hi> but to our greater ſhame, even in the more pure reformed Churches, and at this very inſtant is in the Land of our own Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity: the Subſtance whereof is to this following effect. Whether the Laws of God or man ſhall have the ſuperiority and take place. Whether his <hi>Light</hi> is to be <hi>extinguiſhed,</hi> and his <hi>Truth ſtifled</hi> which he would ſend out, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 43. 3. <hi>if it ſhould reprove the Darkneſs</hi> and Wickedneſs that is in Palaces and great Houſes, or manifeſt the Error of their corrupt ways. But mention is made, <hi>verſ.</hi> 1. of an <hi>ungodly Nation, and a deceitful and unjuſt Man.</hi> They would <hi>ungod</hi> him, if they could reach up and pull down the High and Lofty One, or lead away captive (as hath been done with dumb Idols) the living and Almighty God; But becauſe that is not in their Power; They will do as far as is ſuffered; They act in oppoſition to the <hi>Father of Lights,</hi> James. 1. 17. and do what lieth in them to prevent the riſing of <hi>the Sun of Righteouſneſs;</hi> and afterwards ſtop out the ſhining Thereof. When he that dwelleth between the <hi>Cherubims</hi> would <hi>ſhine forth</hi> Pſal. 80. 1. They will hinder it what they can; But God doth ſuffer it ſo far, for the next thing is, <hi>he will ſtir up his ſtrength</hi> verſ. 2. and then poor Creatures, who now provoke the Lord to Jealouſie, will find that they are not ſtronger then he: in this their ſhort time, they will not bear that word which convinces of Sin and Unrighteouſneſs; But how then will they endure his Indignation and Puniſhment; which that was to warn them of, and put them in a way how they might eſcape. <hi>Even thy Truth O my God.</hi> Pſal. 71. 22. is called a <hi>falſe and feigned libel,</hi> if it doth diſcover their own Falſhood and Hypocriſie. And it muſt skulk about in Corners, or be conveyed in a ſecret place, though there is ſtampt upon it the Image and ſuperſcription of the Great and Inviſible King; but they are <hi>fearful,</hi> Rev. 21. 8. to own and confeſs it before the World; for they fear the Diſpleaſure of Men more then the Diſpleaſure of God. They would have Gods ſervice be brought down to Mans purpoſes, and be ſo modelled as to be made conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtent with the fooliſh policy and miſapprehended welfare of a Nation. Theſe things are ſtrange to mention, but themſelves know, that their inward Thought, Pride and Rebellion of Heart is, that though they will acknowledge with their Tongue and Lips that the <hi>Moſt high ruleth over the Kingdoms of Men, and his Dominion is above and over all;</hi> yet they would have it ſo far come under theirs, That if Gods Laws are contrary, and not agreeable to humane conſtitutions, They muſt not be ſpoken of <note place="margin">Amos 7. 13.</note> nor laid before our Princes and our Prieſts, our Lords and Counſellers for fear of Puniſhment and being proſecuted as one againſt the Government; when <hi>them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in this very thing are againſt the Government of their God.</hi> Alas! How do a ſmall Number of Graſhoppers here on the Earth think of, and would do towards the great Lord of the World? How do men that ſhall die, and muſt appear before him in judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, demean themſelves towards him now they are but a little while in the way? <hi>Ariſe O Lord, let not man prevail, let the Heathen be judged in thy ſight, Put them in fear O Lord, that the Nations may know themſelves to be but men.</hi> Pſal. 9. 19, 20. Again thus much is ſignified by what is written, <hi>He ruleth by his Power for ever, his Eyes behold the Nations: let not the Rebellious exalt themſelves,</hi> Pſal. 66. 7. And though the Nations be never ſo angry, yet now is the time come that God ſhall take to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf <note place="margin">Pſal. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> Great Power and Reign. A little opening and appearance thereof doth now begin in this place and Nation, which will be likewiſe followed in the Habitable parts of the Earth.</p>
            <p>For the matter of contention is not ſo much between the two Kings, who are both Pot-ſherds of the Earth, and ſhall each of them ſeverall be brought down to the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:35589:7"/> bars of the Pit, although now they have their Armies and cauſe their Terrour in the Land of the Living. Ceaſe ye from man whoſe Breath is in his Noſtrils, for wherein is he to be accounted of? We ought utterly to draw off from the Perſons of each, and not to have them in admiration, and not name them more then needs muſt; for by ſo doing men do forget and loſe the knowledge and fear of the Lord; and are not ſo ſenſible of the Glory of his Majeſty and infinite Greatneſs. But the thing which the Lord doth require of our <hi>Land</hi> is, that ſhe do not depart from and for ſake his Eternal and Immutable Rules of Judgment and Righteouſneſs, and that his People be <hi>very couragious to keep and to do all that is written in the Law of</hi> Moſes, <hi>that ye turn not aſide therefrom to the right hand or to the left,</hi> Joſh. 23. 6. So whatever is further com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded in the Book of Pſalms, the Writings of the Prophets, and the Goſpel of Chriſt declared by the <hi>Evangeliſts</hi> and <hi>Apoſtles.</hi> All things are to be done according to his revealed Will, now a little before he ariſeth to ſhake terribly the Earth; <hi>for the Word of the Lord is right, and all his Works are done in truth, he loveth Righteouſneſs and Judgment</hi> Pſal. 33. 4. 5. <hi>Righteouſneſs ſhall go before him, and ſhall ſet us in the way of his Steps.</hi> Pſal. 85. 13. Gods Work ought to b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> done in his own preſcribed method, according to what is written, which is ſo plain and eaſie to be underſtood, that way<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faring men, though Fools, ſhall not err therein, unleſs they run out of willing and ſet purpoſe.</p>
            <p>Whereas heretofore we were diſobedient; and did not all things according to the Pattern ſhewed us; we are to acknowledge our Iniquity and Tranſgreſſion, and from henceforth ſorever, we and our Children are to promiſe unto the Lord and keep it, to do according as he hath ſaid and commanded in his <hi>Word;</hi> which we ought in like manner to obey, as if we heard his Voice from Heaven. As we daily Pray, ſo we are likewiſe to do (leſt we be found Mockers and Diſſemblers with God, and have our portion with Hypocrites and Unbelievers) his will on Earth. Which again is not to be meaſured by what is acted on this ſtage of Sin and Confuſion, or publickly done in the place where Satan's Seat and Kingdom is; but as it is clearly written and manifeſtly revealed by the Word and Spirit of God, which came down from above, and knoweth what is God's will. And what is done in Heaven, the fanie is expected here.</p>
            <p>In the Mouth of two or three Witneſſes every Word ſhall be eſtabliſhed; and we have three holy Men of God, who were moved by the holy Ghoſt, and give at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation and confirmation to the ſame thing. <hi>He is the Rock, his work is perfect, for all his ways are Judgment, a God of Truth, and without Iniquity, juſt and right is be,</hi> Deut. 32. 4. <hi>The Works of his Hands are Verity and Judgment, and all his Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are ſure: They ſtand faſt forever and ever, and are done in Truth and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>prightneſs,</hi> Pſal. 111. 7, 8. By this it appears, that our late Revolution is none of God's work, in which he is well pleaſed. <hi>For I the Lord love Judgment, I hate Robbery for burnt Offering; and I will direct their work in Truth, and I will make an Everlaſting Covenant with them,</hi> Iſa. 61. 8. So that if People would do the work of God, and come to ſettlement and ſtability of Times; they muſt only uſe ſuch means all along as are good, true, juſt and lawful, and none others. Theſe are to be known by God's Law only; for (as aforeſaid) that is the ſupream Rule of Good and Evil, Truth and Falſhood, Right and Wrong.</p>
            <p>And if thence it doth appear, that this Nation hath <hi>treſpaſſed againſt their God,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 58. 2.</note> and have <hi>forſaken</hi> and <hi>reſiſted his Ordinance</hi> by putting down <hi>that Power</hi> (which is aſſerted, Rom. 13. 1. <hi>to be of God,</hi> though it was an Heathen at the very time)
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:35589:7"/> If this be a Sin and Tranſgreſſion, then there is no hope to avoid the preſent Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure, and eſcape the future Puniſhment of God, otherwiſe than by <hi>making a Covenant with our God, and by reſtoring the King to his right; and henceforward to tremble at the Commandments of our God, and l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t it be done according to his Law,</hi> Ezra. 10. 3. The Laws of God are to be ſet before People; and they are to be exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the Obſervance of them; but ſtill men have their Liberty and full Freedom of Action. If they will not do ſo out of Conſcience and Obedience to God, they may let it alone; Or (to ſpeak plainly, deliberately and truly in the Gentile dialect) <hi>chooſe and be damned,</hi> according to what they have done, and involved themſelves in from <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. 2. It is at their own Peril and Danger. The divine Promiſes and Threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings are to be uſed only; but no outward force and compulſion, for the right Chriſtian Religion doth not allow of any. And here is a Threatning as true as Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, which lies expreſly againſt the Nation and People of <hi>England.</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Which I would not have againſt my own par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Perſon for ten thouſand Kingdoms, or the greateſt Places of Honour and Profit, and I would more fear it than to dye an hundred Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral Deaths.</note> 
               <hi>The Wrath of God is revealed from Heaven a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nrighteouſneſs of Men, who hold the Truth in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſs,</hi> Rom. 1. 18. It is only <hi>revealed</hi> and <hi>made known</hi> here; but it is to be <hi>executed</hi> and <hi>felt</hi> in another Place. So though We are in the true Reformed Religion; yet We are not (under the aforeſaid Penalty)<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to continue and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe any Unrighteouſneſs towards our King, who is a Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of a falſe, ſuperſtitious and corrupted Church. <hi>Thou that abborreſt Idols, doſt thou commit Sacriledge?</hi> So they ſhould not commit any Injuſtice, Wrong, Sin or Evil. <hi>Thou that mak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt thy boaſt of the Law through breaking of the Law, Diſhonoureſt thou God? for the Name of God is blaſphemed among the Gentiles through you.</hi> In this National Corruption there have been no leſs than five Laws of the ſecond Table expreſly vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated, as by <hi>Diſhonouring of and Diſobedience to Parents, Committing of Murder, Theft, bearing Falſe Witneſs, Coveting and taking poſſeſſion of anothers Inheritance,</hi> who was greater than <hi>Naboth,</hi> and his inferiour did it. Again, if the <hi>ſolemn Oath hath been de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed, and the Covenant broken</hi> (whereof God alone is to judge and determine of both ſides) then as ſure as God is (which is as evident as the Heavens He created and we ſee, or that he laid the Foundations of the Earth which we tread on) ſo certainly will <hi>He recompence it upon their own Head.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Unleſs all this is prevented by true and unfeigned Repentance, in order to which it is neceſſary not only to be ſorry, or ſecretly to bewail, but further to undo the Fault as much as it can be. And as God was diſhonoured publickly, in like manner to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain his Favour. They ſhould publickly acknowledge their Iniquity to their God, that they have tranſgreſſed againſt him by forſaking his Ordinance, deſpiſing his Oath, and breaking his Covenant. To ſpeak after the manner of men, That God ſhould have repair for his hurt Majeſty, which they offended and deſpiſed, and alſo have Glory given unto him by confeſſing their own ſhame; for we muſt do as much to reconcile our ſelves to an offended God, as the Great Ones of the Earth require from all that diſpleaſe them. And this is the true deſign and end of Confeſſion. Thoſe Things done in Private, may be there acknowledged; but in other Things, the acknowledgment ſhould be altogether as Publick as the ſin was, according to Lev. 26. 40. Joſh. 7. 19. Ezra 10. 2, 3, 10, 11. Mark 1. 5. Acts 19. 18. And where <hi>any thing hath been taken away from any man by Falſe Accuſation,</hi> He is to be reſtored to it again; and the very Truth of all Things to be brought out, and to be known
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:35589:8"/> openly before the World. It might be ſo ordered and conſented unto, That They have Deputies, faithful, couragious and learned, to implead one another before the Great Council of the Nation, and Witneſſes examined upon Oath of both ſides. Which would be a more Chriſtian and Rational way, than to lead forth Armies to puſh at and gore one another, like a <hi>Multitude of Bulls and Calves of the People,</hi> Pſal. 68. 30. Man was born more naked and unarmed than thoſe dull Creatures; but they have found Inſtruments of Death to knock down and butcher one another.</p>
            <p>And though in theſe days of Wickedneſs and Ignorance there is ſuch <hi>truſting in the Arm of Fleſh,</hi> and <hi>Children do riſe up againſt their Parents,</hi> to cauſe them to be put to Death, and ſanctifie it with a Faſt, and then again after the Turkiſh manner, conclude of the Righteouſneſs of their Cauſe by the Succeſs and event thereof: Or think to eſcape becauſe they fulfill the Scriptures, whereas <hi>Judas</hi> did the ſame. But the ſame Word ſaith, It would have been good for him if he had never been born. We are not to be ſurprized or doubtful as to this; for it was the Queſtion of old time, <hi>Wherefore doth the way of the wick<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d Proſper? wherefore are all they happy that deal very treacherouſly? Thou haſt planted them, yea, they have taken root, they grow, yea, they bring forth fruit,</hi> Jer. 12. 1. 2. And they keep for a while what they obtain by lying <hi>Flatteries,</hi> (Dan. 11. 21.) Diſſimulation, Carnal Policy and Wiſdom. But if theſe were detected, the other would not ſtand and endure. As may be gathered (let him that readeth, underſtand) from what is ſpoken of in the Prophet <hi>Daniel, It caſt down the Truth to the Ground, and it practiſed and proſpered,</hi> Dan. 8. 12. And then indeed Tranſgreſſion may prevail and ſpread abroad. But if Truth were not fallen in the Street, and Equity could enter; if Truth might once maintain its Ground, and Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs take place; if as ſoon as the <hi>Lord gave the Word, great would be the company of thoſe that publiſhed it,</hi> Pſal. 68. 11. The next immediate conſequence is, <hi>Kings of Armies did flee apace,</hi> Verſ. 12. And in a little proceſs of Time it would be ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled all the World over; <hi>for lo, the Kings were aſſembled, they paſſed by together, they ſaw it, and ſo they marvelled; They were troubled and haſted away; Fear took hold upon them there, and Pain as of a Woman in Travail,</hi> Pſal. 48. 4. 5. 6. And though now the Kings ſet themſelves, and the Rulers take counſel together againſt the Lord, and againſt his anointed; yet his ſingle Word and Truth, if it had a free courſe and univerſal ſpreading, would ſcatter them all.</p>
            <p>As of old Time, when the Lord looked into the Hoſt of the <hi>Egytians,</hi> through the Pillar of Fire and of the Cloud, he troubled the Hoſt of the <hi>Egyptians;</hi> ſo it is now at this very day. When he ſends forth a Manifeſtation of his Word, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>playes a <hi>Banner of Truth</hi> (which is always done by ſome outward Inſtrument) it doth cauſe Diſturbance in the Minds of Men, and is thought to break their Peace, becauſe it doth ſomewhat interrupt their ſecurity and ignorance in Sin. It doth fill their Souls with fear and doubt, and there is a worſe reſtleſneſs within then Swords and Staves do cauſe among the multitude. And this is but a flight and tranſient fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runner of that <hi>Indignation and Wrath, Tribulation and Anguiſh, which ſhall be upon thoſe who are Contentious, and do not obey the Truth, but obey <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nrighteouſneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Indeed ſuch may be mad, or fooliſh and inconſiderate, but they can never be tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly couragious, unleſs they are ſtupefied, and made blind by Drunkenneſs, Pride, Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belief, groſs Ignorance: And when this laſt a little wears off, they are furniſhed with <hi>ſtrong Deluſions</hi> that they ſhould believe a Lye; They receive in falſe and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake Notions; or they are feared by the cloſe hidden acts of Hypocriſie. For they cannot endure to conſider of throughly what is commanded, <hi>That no man.</hi> (of what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:35589:8"/> rank or degree) <hi>go beyond and defraud his Brother</hi> (muchleſs a Father) <hi>in any matter, becauſe that the Lord is the avenger of all ſuch; as we have alſo fore warned you and teſtified,</hi> 1 Theſ. 4. 6. now this third time. And they being upon the brink to appear before that God, and (as we are here told) ſubject to Evils from the World to come; It is a marvellous Policy and deſtructive Miſchief ſo to beguile that they fall in before they took any care to prevent, or were throughly put in mind, and tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly informed hereof. It muſt be barbarous, and a fiding with the Deceiver of mankind, to contrive on ſet purpoſe to keep People ignorant; and as they think for the better accompliſhment of a preſent Deſign to ſuffer ſo many to fall into the future miſery, and to let them periſh and be deſtroyed for want of the right knowledge of things. A report and glimps of Eternity will more ſtartle than the flaſhing and noiſe of Guns, and the doubtful uncertainty of what kind of endleſs Life they are juſt entring upon, will cauſe <hi>great Thought and ſearching of Heart;</hi> which is more ſenſible than Wounds and Blows to the outward Man: For it is at their Peril (without fooliſh Jeſting, or meer outward Laughter, or a proud contemptuous Smile) if the Kings of the Earth, and the Great Men, and the Rich Men, and the Chief Captains, and the Mighty Men ſhould not obey the Goſpel of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt; for ſuch will hide and fear as much as they brave it out, and ſeem reſolute now. But if they would indeed be preſerved from the Wrath of the Lamb, they muſt yield Obedience unto what He hath commanded in the Goſpel. <hi>Therefore all things whatſoever ye would that Men ſhould do unto you, do ye even ſo to them, for this is the Law and the Prophets,</hi> Mat. 7. 12. <hi>If it be poſſible, as much as lieth in you, live peaceably with all men,</hi> Rom. 12. 18. <hi>Render therefore to all their Dues,</hi> Rom. 13. 7. All fair and honeſt means ought to be uſed, firſt to prevent thoſe miſchievous effects of Bloodſhed, Poverty, Sickneſs, continual Fears, which may terminate in temporal Deſolation and eternal Deſtruction. And even now theſe <hi>Wounds,</hi> and <hi>Bruiſes,</hi> and <hi>putrifying Sores</hi> are broke out, they may yet be <hi>cloſed, and bound up and mollified with Oyntment,</hi> inſtead of the long, ſevere and deſtructive Remedies. And if men will not do according to the Will of God, and of Chriſt, take heed leſt that alſo come upon you, which is ſpoken of in the following Verſe, <hi>Your Country is deſolate, your Cities are burnt with Fire; your Land ſtrangers devour it in your preſence, and it is deſolate as overthrown by Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers,</hi> Iſa. 1. 7. When a Fire or Plague is begun, People do endeavour to extinguiſh and ſtop it as ſoon as they can. The drawn Sword may be put up in its Sheath, and the grievouſneſs of War might ceaſe; and (as aforeſaid) Things ſhould be done by way of juſt Treaty, and prudent Accomodation.</p>
            <p>I am for Peace, but when I ſpeak, they are for War: Nay, They will do pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſely, and more violently againſt what is here ſaid, becauſe Theſe things are laid together by a ſmall and deſpicable Perſon, whoſe Spirit God hath ſtirred and raiſed him up as an Inſtrument to convey forth <hi>his Truth</hi> unto Men; for <hi>I ſpeak nothing of my ſelf, but from his Word only.</hi> And therefore their Murmuring, and Deſpiſing, and Rebellion are <hi>againſt the Lord.</hi> This ought to be done by ſome one, yea, and by many. But whoever had firſt appeared to cry aloud, and ſpare not; Lift up thy Voice like a Trumpet to ſhew the People of <hi>England</hi> their Tranſgreſſions and their Sins; The ſame Reproaches and falſe Suggeſtions would have been againſt them alſo. For when People have no mind to receive and obey the Meſſage, it is eaſie to take exceptions at the Poſt or Officer who brings it. But the all-knowing and all-wiſe God will not be trifled with, nor deceived: The Great King of all the Earth will find and bring out thoſe his Enemies, who <hi>would not have him Reign over them,</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:35589:9" rendition="simple:additions"/> but do ſpeak againſt, and evil intreat the Meſſengers whom he hath ſent:</p>
            <p>And now to manifeſt unto the World that I am <hi>ſent,</hi> and to make <hi>evident my C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion,</hi> I do declare (as I will anſwer it before him who is appointed Judge of the quick and dead) that it is contained in the twenty third Chapter of <hi>Mathew,</hi> and the thirty fourth Verſe, where Chriſt promiſes to the ſeveral Generations, <hi>Behold I ſend</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Acts 2. 39</note> 
               <hi>unto you Prophets, and Wiſemen, &amp; Scribes.</hi> And I do affirm according to Truth, without boaſting of my ſelf, that I do come under the laſt denomination of a <hi>Scribe.</hi> I may juſt obſerve, that the Prophetical Office was chiefly to reprove Sin and Tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and alſo they did fore-tell ſome future events which were not preſently ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled. The firſt hath been done without Partiality and Reſpect of Perſons; and alſo ſome things have been ſpoken of, which are yet to come. Moreover if there have been any Words of Knowledge and Wiſdom delivered, let others judge. But a <hi>Scribe</hi> is ſuch an one who is inſtructed in, and reaſons out of the Law; which is the very ſame what I have done as to National Affairs: For the ſeveral things which I have publiſhed to the World are an opening, and alledging, and reaſoning out of the Scriptures, the Law of the Moſt high God.</p>
            <p>I have been educated at the School of the Prophets; for I was ſix Years at <hi>Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalen Hall in Oxford,</hi> and took one degree: I was there twice ſworn the Oath of Allegiance and Supremacy. And now it comes to paſs that the ſame Oath which ſuch a vaſt multitude of Prieſts and People have deſpiſed, hath taken hold of me, and hath obliged me to act after this manner. For I did Swear twice in the Reign of <hi>Charles the ſecond, Him and them (innuendo</hi> his Heirs and Succeſſors, under which his <hi>Brother</hi> is compriſed) <hi>will I defend, according to the utmoſt of my Power.</hi> Now the Weapons of our Warfare are not Carnal, but Spiritual, and no other ought to be uſed according to the right Chriſtian Religion. For theſe laſt ſix Years I have been at ſeveral times reſident in and about the City of <hi>London:</hi> I was entred into the Society of the <hi>Middle Temple,</hi> and obſerved the Cuſtoms of the Houſe for ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral ſucceſſive Terms; and I did for a while ſtudy the Statute and Common Laws of this Nation: So that I came all along in a regular way, and was furniſhed from the Laws of God and Man, to have pleaded the Cauſe of the <hi>Oppreſſed King.</hi> And for my part, being aſſured only of the Protection of the inviſible God, and truſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to that Promiſe, <hi>His Truth ſhall be thy Shield and Buckler,</hi> Pſal. 91. 4. I was not afraid to ſpeak openly and boldly as I ought to ſpeak. Though both Houſes of Parliament, by reaſon of contrary Practice (as may be underſtood from <hi>Jer.</hi> 2. 26. <hi>Mark</hi> 8. 38.) were <hi>aſhamed to hear ſuch Words;</hi> which would have reproved, and ſet in order before them their Sin and Tranſgreſſion in the very ſame place where it was committed. And ſo they may ſtill, if they are willing to run the danger of <hi>riſing up to everlaſting Shame and Contempt,</hi> and have the <hi>Son of man be aſhamed of them, when he cometh in the Glory of his Father with the holy Ang<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ls.</hi> ſaith the Lord, <hi>And it ſhall come to paſs, that whoſoever will not hearken to my Words which he ſhall ſpeak in my Name, I will require it of him,</hi> Deut. 18. 19. Now that Prophet was <hi>Chriſt,</hi> who hath conveyed down to others the ſame Authority and Commiſſion, <hi>He that heareth you, heareth me; and he that deſpiſeth you, deſpiſeth me; and he that deſpiſeth me, deſpiſeth him that ſent me,</hi> Luke 10. 16. For ſuch would not hear Chriſt himſelf, if they had lived in the ſame Generation with him; Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther would they be perſwaded, if <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſhould come once again into the World af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the ſame manner as he did; But his next coming is unto Judgment.</p>
            <p>Peradventure, our Lords and Counſellors did go upon Error and Deceit of their
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:35589:9"/> own Heart, and did therefore refuſe to hear the Law of their God; becauſe they might think that if the <hi>Word</hi> was not <hi>proclaimed</hi> and ſpoken out <hi>viva voce,</hi> They might then more ſafely contemn God's Word and Commandment, and have ſuch a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> excuſe for their Sin; not conſidering the God with whom we have to do: <hi>Who un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtands our Thoughts afar off,</hi> Pſal. 139. 2. and knows that themſelves only hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, and would not ſuffer his Word to be ſpoken out. For I delivered in Print<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Caſes, and alſo ſent a written Petition to the ſame purpoſe: And when I could not have it delivered in and read, I ordered my Petition to be printed and given to the Members ſeverally (if perhaps any would move thereon) though I knew before this was contrary to Cuſtom and Uſage, and therefore I was at firſt unwilling ſo to do; but this kind of neceſſity and urgency did preſs me forward. For my part I would leave no means undone to diſcharge my Conſcience fully to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God: But He knows that I was directed and put in mind long before, <hi>That this is a rebellious People, lying Children, Children that will not hear the Law of the Lord,</hi> Iſa. 30. 9. And thereupon according to what is ſaid in the foregoing Verſe, and alſo I was ſhewed the ſame in the Light of God's Spirit, <hi>Now go and get it print<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in a Book;</hi> which I accordingly did, and delivered to the ſeveral Members on <hi>April</hi> 2. 1690. for which I was committed to Cuſtody (it being by them called a Seditious Pamphlet) and ſo I remained under confinement for four Weeks, and afterwards was with great care ſent down into the Country, to be remote from <hi>London.</hi> I gave away about an hundred of thoſe ſtitcht Books, and would have more ready if I had been permitted; for I ordered a thouſand, which were more then ſufficient for all the Repreſentatives of the whole Nation: But however, they had ſufficient to notifie it unto the reſidue of the Members; and they may yet un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand and be inſtructed aright, that the <hi>Word</hi> (which God ſends through a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible earthen Veſſel) <hi>ſpoken</hi> (or written, for that longer remains) <hi>is ſtedfaſt, and every Tranſgreſſion and Diſobedience ſhall receive a juſt recompence of Reward.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As they do all profeſs themſelves to be Members of the <hi>Church of England,</hi> ſo they are to be advertiſed of ſomewhat out of her Liturgy in the Exhortation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Communion; <hi>Therefore if any of you be a Blaſphemer of God, an hinderer or ſlanderer of his Word, repent you of your Sins, or elſe come not to that holy Table.</hi> But becauſe ye have the outward Adminiſtration thereof in your own Power; and your Biſhops, Prieſts and Deacons are involved in, and carried away with the ſame corruption; They will nevertheleſs diſpence the Holy Sacrament unto you, though ye do ſtill continue in and practice the ſame Sins. But yet be ye aſſured and fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warned from the truth and determination of God, that notwithſtanding ye do ſtill partake of the outward part or ſign, yet ye will be deprived of the thing ſignified thereby: That is, now of the true Grace and Spirit of God, and hereafter (to ſpeak in plain terms) ye will be <hi>excommunicated and ſhut out from Heaven.</hi> And ye can no more enter there againſt his Decree and Will, than now ye can flye up, and of your own ſtrength cauſe the Heavens to be opened to receive you. God will not admit them there, who would not ſuffer him to <hi>reign over them</hi> here on Earth by his Word, and the Meſſengers appointed to publiſh and make it known; who are neceſſary for the exerciſe and adminiſtration of his Kingdom and Dominion over Men. I ſpeak to our Rulers, judge ye in your ſelves. How would any earthly King receive it, to have his Ambaſſadors and Officers, yea, an inferiour Herald or Poſte diſturbed, and interrupt and ſtopt in the execution of his buſineſs? We are his Servants, and muſt do according to what our great Lord and Maſter ſends
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:35589:10"/> us; and if any Injury is offered us, he takes it upon himſelf, and will puniſh ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to <hi>Mark</hi> 12. 4, 5, 9. And if my ſelf ſhould be <hi>killed or ſcourged, or perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted from place to place;</hi> whoſoever ſhall preſume to do it, either ſecretly or open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, God knows it all one, they muſt alſo take what follows, <hi>That upon you may come all the Righteous Blood ſhed upon the Earth,</hi> Mat. 23. 35. The greateſt Emperors, Kings, Princes and Potentates will find one higher than they. The inferiour Judges, Magiſtrates and Officers will meet with one, whom they were as much bound to obey as their reſpective Maſters. Great ſwelling Words will be changed into dole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Cries and Lamentations: Inſtead of domineering and inſulting over thoſe whom they had once Priſoners before them, will ſucceed trembling at their preſence; and ſuch will be ſtrangely abaſhed to ſee them become their Judges. God will ariſe and maintain his own Cauſe, and the boldeſt Perſecutors of them all ſhall at length find, <hi>He that toucheth you, toucheth the Apple of his Eye,</hi> Zech. 2. 8. He had bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter run his own Finger into his own Eyes and bore them out, rather than do thoſe things to be caſt into Hell-Fire. This harſh, but true expreſſion may be further gathered from <hi>Mat.</hi> 18. 6, 7, 8, 9.</p>
            <p>And though it is in a leſs degree of Reproach, Slander or Reviling, Curſes or hard Speeches againſt the Perſon of ſuch an one: Surely men know not, nor conſider what they do herein: <hi>Becauſe for thy ſake I have born Reproach, Shame hath covered my Face: I am become a Stranger unto my Brethren, and an alient unto my Mother's Children. For the Zeal of thine Houſe hath eaten me up: and the Reproaches of them that reproached thee are fallen upon me,</hi> Pſal. 69. 7, 8, 9. To ſpeak againſt, or evil of any one, who doth not handle the Word of God deceitfully, but by manifeſtation of the Truth, commending himſelf to every man's Conſcience in the fight of God, and to recriminate upon the Inſtrument which conveys it forth, becauſe the Word <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces of Sin, and of Righteouſneſs, and of Judgment:</hi> This doth firſt manifeſt their own guilt and contrary practice, and to reply againſt it, is to <hi>reply againſt God,</hi> Rom. 9. 20. It is anſwering again and diſputing, and a kind of blaſpheming the Holy One of <hi>Iſrael:</hi> For ſuch are reſolved not to do the thing, and are ſo far from coming to Repentance, and turning from their Iniquities, that they harden and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm themſelves yet more in their ſinful ways. <hi>They will utter and ſpeak hard things, and the Workers of Iniquity boaſt themſelves,</hi> Pſal. 94. 4. ſee verſ. 20. And theſe are the <hi>hard Speeches which <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ngodly Sinners have ſpoken againſt him,</hi> Jude 15. This ſhews the exceeding ſinfulneſs of Reproach, which hath more or leſs aggravation, according to the particular kind, of <note n="*" place="margin">Jer. 18. 18.</note> ſayings; which were invented and promoted by the Father of Lyes; who is ſuffered to <hi>reſiſt the Servants of God,</hi> and doth it with an intent and purpoſe to make them as Lyars, and through them to derogate from God's Glory and Truth; that, if poſſible, the Word which goeth forth out of his Mouth ſhould return to him void, and not accompliſh that which he pleaſes, nor proſper in the thing whereto he ſends it: for to this tend the Devices and Wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Satan, the adverſary of God's Kingdom.</p>
            <p>But let thoſe who have any reverence or fear of God, take heed how they ſpeak of him and <hi>his Truth,</hi> which appears forth through his Servant: for that indeed, and not ſo much the outward Perſon, is the Thing chiefly admired at. <hi>I am as a Won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> (in the new Tranſlation it is Monſter) <hi>unto many; but thou art my ſtrong Refuge,</hi> Pſal 71. 7. <hi>For whether we be beſides our ſelves, it is to God,</hi> 2 Cor. 5. 13. Chriſt himſelf had the imputation of Madneſs. <hi>And when his Friends</hi> (in the Marginal Reading it is Kinsmen) <hi>heard of it, they went out to lay hold on him; for they ſaid,</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:35589:10"/> 
               <hi>He is beſides himſelf,</hi> Mark 3. 21. The Scribes who underſtood a little more, did blaſpheme againſt the Holy Ghoſt, <hi>becauſe they ſaid, he hath an unclean Spirit,</hi> Verſ. 30. And to ſay, ſuch an one is an <hi>But buſiaſt</hi> or <hi>Fanatick,</hi> in the plain and proper ſignification is to affirm, He is poſſeſt with the Spirit of the Devil, ſuch as did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide amongſt the <hi>Oracles of Old,</hi> or in the <hi>Heathen Temples:</hi> And therefore though it be a gentile and haſty Word, People ſhould be exceeding cautious on whom they affix it. For we muſt expunge many places out of Scripture, confirmed by expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience, if we deny the workings of God's Spirit in theſe dayes; but it is ſubject unto, &amp; keeps within the bounds of his Revelation. And then if this or that Perſon ſhould have the true Spirit of God and of Chriſt, it would be the very ſame Blaſphemy. But if they have called the Maſter of the Houſhold <hi>Belzebub;</hi> much more will they call thoſe of the Houſhold. We read again, that Himſelf hath the ſame double Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach caſt on him: <hi>And many of them ſaid, He hath a Devil, and is mad; why hear ye him?</hi> John 10. 20. If we go back to the Old Teſtament, we ſhall find ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what to the ſame purpoſe. The young man, the Prophet, was thus ſtiled by one of the Captains of the Hoſt that were ſitting, <hi>Wherefore came this mad fellow to thee?</hi> 2 Kings 9. 11. A ſhort queſtion, and exactly agreeable to the Language of the proud men of theſe dayes. Again, we read of one who ſent Letters unto all the People who are at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and to <hi>Zepheniah</hi> the Son of <hi>Maſaiah</hi> the Prieſt, and to all the Prieſts to put them in mind; whereas they were <hi>Officers in the Houſe of the Lord for every man that is mad, and maketh himſelf a Prophet; that thou ſhouldſt put him in Priſon, and in the Stocks; Now therefore why haſt thou not reproved</hi> Jeremiah, <hi>of An<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>thoth, which maketh himſelf a Prophet to you?</hi> Jer. 29. 25, 26, 27. But it may be afterwards ſeen in the following Verſes what is pronounced on <hi>Shemaiah</hi> the <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>helamite,</hi> becauſe he thus <hi>taught Rebellion againſt the Lord.</hi> Again, it is written, <hi>The Prophet is a fool, The Spiritual Man is mad, for the multitude of thine Iniquity, and the great Hatred,</hi> Hoſ. 9. 7. Here is added the very reaſon of throwing out ſuch a falſe Reproach, viz. <hi>Multitude of Iniquity and Great Hatred;</hi> for ſin, when it is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, doth leave guilt behind: And when it comes to be reproved and manifeſted, that is ſtirred up: And then there is Conviction, Shame, Fear and Anguiſh of Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit; all which are very troubleſome and diſquieting, and thence doth ariſe an hatred and enmity againſt ſuch who do this Office. Saith our Lord and Saviour, <hi>The World ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth me, becauſe I Teſtifie of it that the Works thereof are evil,</hi> Joh. 7. 7. But they deſerve more to be hated who do the evil, then Chriſt who Teſtifieth of it. <hi>Bleſſed are ye when Men ſhall hate you, and when they ſhall ſeparate you from their Company, and ſhall reproach you, and caſt out your Name as evil, for the Son of Mans ſake</hi> (for doing ſo, as we have him and them for an Example) <hi>In the like manner did their Fathers unto the Prophets,</hi> Luk. 6. 22. 23. <hi>Bleſſed are they which are perſecuted for Righteouſneſs ſake: Bleſſed are ye when Men ſhall revile you, and perſecute you, and ſhall ſay all manner of evil againſt you falſly for my ſake,</hi> Mat. 5. 10, 11. for being faithful in that Miniſtry to which he hath called us. Here it is moſt comprehenſively expreſſed, and extends unto all manner of evil and falſhood, which the utmoſt wit and malice of limited Creatures can invent and ſpeak forth. And therefore if ſuch an one it of a ſound mind and clear underſtanding (I ſpeak of my ſelf, and of the Things which I have written touching the King) It is a contradiction and abominable lie to ſay, he is <hi>non compos Mentis;</hi> But yet a malicious and falſe imputation may be caſt and endeavoured to be faſtened on any one. And alſo, what is a little new or unuſual, or doth ſomewhat exceed common apprehenſion, may ſeem to the vulgar ſort, yea, and be called by them mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs;
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:35589:11"/> but this is ſo trivial, that it is ſufficient anſwer only to take notice of ſuch an Ignorant Calumny.</p>
            <p>I am liable to be repreſented, as one of different Notions, becauſe of a different ſhape by reaſon of my perſonal Deformity and Lameneſs; whereby I do vary ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what from the reſt of mankind. But the Lord is the Maker of us all. And he who faſhioned me in the Womb, and took me out of my Mother's Bowels, might have ſo formed them who either have already, or ſhall reproach me in this wiſe. They are to remember, that themſelves alſo are in the Body ſubject to ſickneſs from within, to Hurt and Caſualty from without. I was not born ſo for mine own Sin, nor for my Parents, but that the Works of God ſhould be mad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> manifeſt. And it may be the more remembred (I hope not for a Witneſs and Teſtimony againſt them) that ſuch an one came down to the place of the whole Aſſembly of this Nation, with <hi>the Truth which God bad ſhewed unto his Servant, and with his Staff in his Hand:</hi> He had no other <note place="margin">Gen. 32. 10.</note> Weapon, and would not have had that, but he went <hi>Halting</hi> as did the <hi>Patriarke</hi> whoſe words are here made uſe off. And this will be a further ſign and token, that they cannot pretend Ignorance of the man, or his buſineſs in the day of Recapitulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of all things.</p>
            <p>But the greater ſtrangeneſs is imagined to be within me; <hi>I have written the great things of thy Law, but they were counted as a ſtrange thing,</hi> Hoſ. 8. 12. ſaid the Prophet in his time; and within the compaſs of this year, the like imputation hath been caſt upon my particular Perſon, for what I have brought out of the ſame Book of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. But to <hi>cauſe the Reproach offered by them to ceaſe, and to turn their own reproach upon them,</hi> Dan. 11. 18. I will tell any one that thinks ſo, where the ſtrangeneſs of all lieth, <hi>even in Mans Tranſgreſſion.</hi> Either the not obſervance of what is command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, or doing thoſe things which are contrary to the Laws of God and Truth. In Tranſgreſſing and Lying againſt the Lord, and departing away from our God, ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing oppreſſion and revolt, conceiving and uttering from the Heart words of falſhood. By not doing of Righteouſneſs, but forſaking the Ordinance of their God, nor taking heed to the Ordinances of Juſtice. It is Mens ſtrange kind of actions, which do draw and neceſſitate from my Tongue and Pen what may ſeem ſtrange kind of expreſſions: For I do only ſpeak of them according to their very nature, and as they are done. But more eſpecially when the Thoughts of their Heart come to be revealed, and thoſe ſecret imaginations are made known by that Word which is a diſcernes of the Thoughts and intents of the Heart, there muſt be yet more ſtrange kind of expreſſions, odd paſtages, uncouth, uncommon, they know not what to make off or term them. If one ſhould mention how they fret themſelves, and are apt to curſe their God and their King, It would paſs for an hard ſaying; when all this is far worſe in them that do it, then in thoſe who only take notice thereof in order to admoniſh them to ſtand in aw and Sin not. All the ſtrangeneſs is in themſelves; and accordingly the Spirit who ſearches all things and ſpeaks the very Truth, calls them <hi>ſtrange Children,</hi> Pſal. 144. 11. For nothing can be more ſtrange then that Man ſhould be Diſobedient to his God, that the Children which the Lord hath brought up ſhould rebel againſt him. But further they muſt be known, and alſo ſpoken forth in order to the caſting down Imaginations, and every high thing that exalteth it ſelf againſt the knowledge of God, and bringing into captivity every Thought to the Obedience of Chriſt. When theſe Imaginations and Thoughts are clearly and truly brought out to publick view; they quite fall to the Ground, and never riſe again.</p>
            <p>I appeal to any one who knows Truth, and can apprehend common ſence that in
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:35589:11"/> the ſeveral things I have publiſhed to the World, I have all along delivered my ſelf in plain, common, obvious, familiar and intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligible Expreſſions. I have ſpoken forth the <hi>Words of Truth and Sober<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs;</hi> though it is hard to expreſs the mad and fooliſh Actions of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind to the very Life and Reality, and not to be reputed ſo ones ſelf. All <hi>thoſe that fear God, and thoſe that have known his Teſtimonies,</hi> Pſal. 119. 79. can alſo judge of theſe things. And though what I have more lately done, in oppoſing the High and Univerſal Corruption of this preſent Time, hath met with Strife and Contention, S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bornneſs and deſpiſing, all kinds of Reproach and contrary Uſage; yet the Reaſon of all is, becauſe People <hi>are Contentions, and do not obey the Truth, but obey <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nrighteouſneſs,</hi> Rom. 2. 8. They have <hi>made void God's Law,</hi> Pſal. 119. 126. and his Commandments of none effect: <hi>Therefore the Law is ſlacked, and Judgment doth never go forth; for the Wicked doth compaſs about the Righteous, therefore wrong Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment proceedeth,</hi> Hab. 1. 4. For they have indeed acted contrary to what the Law commands and requires. Nevertheleſs, all knowing People may yet judge of whatever I have here ſaid, or in the two fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited Treatiſes concerning our Great National Sin and Tranſgreſſion, by this certain and infallible Rule of the Prophet, <hi>That we might turn from our Iniquities, and underſtand thy Truth,</hi> Dan. 9. 13. Then it will appear unto them, as clear and evident, as the moſt plain and ſimple propoſition now doth. If People will not do this, but go on ſtill with all deceiveableneſs of Unrighteouſneſs, there is no Remedy, but they ſhall periſh. <hi>Becauſe they received not the love of the Truth, that they might be ſaved; and for this cauſe God ſhall ſend them ſtrong Deluſions, that they ſhould believe a Lye: That they all might be damned, who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved not the Truth, but had Pleaſure in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nrighteouſneſs,</hi> 2 Theſ. 2. 10, 11, 12. All which Words are obſervable, and very terrible.</p>
            <p>To unfold the <hi>Myſtery of Iniquity</hi> a little, and ſomewhat to lay open the working of Satan with all <hi>deceiveableneſs of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nrighteouſneſs:</hi> It will be neceſſary to obſerve with what kind of words he tempted our Parent in the firſt Tranſgreſſion; and hath all along, and doth yet continually ſet himſelf againſt God's ways, to keep up the miſt of Ignorance and Unbellef, to hold people in their Perplexity and Confuſion of Diſobedience and Tranſgreſſion; and he doth uſe all means to hinder men from coming to Repentance, and the <hi>Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the Truth.</hi> And as God would accompliſh that by right Words, ſo he doth endeavour to imitate in like things, by tempring Mankind to do after their own Thoughts, and after the Imaginati<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ons of their own Evil and Corrupt Heart: And alſo his Emiſſaries
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:35589:12"/> go about ſubverting People with falſe, corrupt and deceitful Words; which are, and may be publiſhed with Licence and Authority. But the Inhabitants of his Earth are aſhamed, or afraid to receive the <hi>Truth</hi> of him, who is Lord and Governour of the World, who filleth all Places and all Things with his preſence. Poor Creatures! <hi>Your Hour</hi> will quickly be at an end, and the <hi>Power of Darkneſs</hi> will be ſuddenly gone off; and then ye ſhall remember and diſcern, which Maſter it was better to have ſerved, God or the World.</p>
            <p>As the <hi>Man of Sin</hi> doth ſo mightily beat off People from the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, becauſe his own Ways and Corruption are ſo much condemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed therein. So do others at this day for the very ſame Reaſon, put an opprobrious term upon the Language of the holy Ghoſt: or it is not ſo gentile and faſhionable, nor agreeable with the Humor of the Age. They cry it out for impertinent and fooliſh; yea, there are an hundred kind of Surmiſes, and like ſayings, whereby <hi>the Word of the Lord is made a Reproach to me, and a Deriſion daily,</hi> Jer 20. 8. They reject and will have none of it. But what ſaith the anſwer of God unto them? <hi>Hear O Earth, Behold I will bring Evil on this People, even the Fruit of their own Thoughts, becauſe they have not hearkened to my Words, nor to my Law, but rejected it,</hi> Jer 6. 19. All their other Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion is vain; their Worſhip and Devotion is to no purpoſe, for it doth not pleaſe God. <hi>Your burnt-Offerings are not acceptable, nor your Sacrifices ſweet unto me,</hi> Verſ. 20. <hi>He that turneth away his Ear from hearing the Law, even his Prayer ſhall be abomination,</hi> Prov. 28. 9. Even at this day, and in this Nation; The Wiſe Men are aſhamed, they are diſmayed and taken; Lo, they have rejected the Word of the Lord, and what Wiſdom is in them? <hi>Jer.</hi> 8. 9. It would be Nonſence, and a Lye to ſay, if one heard a Lawyer cite ſeveral ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs Acts of Parliament, according to the very Sence, and the plain and common Underſtanding of the ſame Words, yet ſuch an one did not argue to the Purpoſe; for all is forreign and impertinent beſides what is thence alledged. And ſo our Great Lawmakers and Counſellors are very fond of the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> own Conſtitutions, to do all things exactly according to the form and direction thereof; But they did not attend, how in the late Revolution, they did at once ſtrike at all the Statute and common Laws of this Kingdom, which are ſaid to be veſted in <hi>Scrinio Regis;</hi> and alſo they did unhinge thoſe very Laws, which do give and adjuſt to themſelves their own reſpective Honours and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates, and eſtabliſh Property; And therefore they ſhould do well to lift the right Door again upon the Hinges. This is Truth, though is may ſeem a kind of Human Reaſoning; but yet doth ſhew how
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:35589:12"/> Judgment is turned away backward, and Juſtice ſtandeth afar off, and Equity cannot enter.</p>
            <p>If our Proud Men think themſelves too good to be Subjects and <note place="margin">Jer. 13. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Servants unto God, yet, whether they will or not, they are his Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures: He is King of Kings, and Lord of Lords. There is no removing the Government off from his Shoulders, nor getting themſelves from under it; as may, and hath been done to the Son of Man. And who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever are ſo ſtout as not to mind Scripture, God's revealed Law, are at this time Tranſgreſſors againſt the ſame, and ſhall be at the laſt day condemned by it. This would be alike ſenſible, if we had the ſame knowledge of him that is inviſible, and conſideration of Futuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, as we have now regard to our Kings and Governours after the Fleſh, and take care for the preſent time; for (as before intimated) the Law of our God is written in a Book, and may in like manner be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood as the Laws, Cuſtoms and Manners of this or that Country we live in.</p>
            <p>There are many Words in the World, and none of them is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Signification; for they have reſpect unto Things; and what ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſes things as they are, the very Nature and Connexion of them together, That is Truth. Now becauſe many of them are hidden, afar off, unſeen, and not heard, it is the office of Reaſon to ſearch them out, and to bring them near by Probability and Witneſſes. So there may be many Words, and a long courſe of Reaſoning to bring out one ſingle Truth. And then oppoſite to Truth and Reaſon, are Falſhood and Imagination. We may evidently perceive that all things are Gods, and that his Word is perfect and true, for that ſpeaks of every thing according to its Nature (either in expreſs Words or juſt Conſequence, though this is many times hidden, and not diſcernable) which belong to mankind, from the greateſt to the leaſt, except what may be known from our ſelves, and the moſt common obſervation. So all is but vain and deceitful Words, which do not ſpring up, nor may be gathered from this ground of Truth. This is left as a ſtanding Rule to try the Doctrines whether they be of men or no. And we may further know Truth by the Underſtanding which is given us: for Truth (if it be clearly apprehended) hath a full conviction over the Heart and Conſcience. Notwithſtanding the ſhifts and tricks, the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puting and crafty eluding, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>et there doth remain a firm perſwaſion in the mind which cannot be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>t off. When the Spirit of the mind ſuggeſts to the man, <hi>This is the ver<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Truth,</hi> it is exceeding dangerous to reſiſt or do deſpite to that; to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>bborn againſt or deſpiſe it, to forget, or be <hi>willingly Ignorant.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:35589:13"/>
            <p> And hence we may learn to take a judgment and eſtimation of the <hi>Wiſdom of man's Words,</hi> fine Flouriſhes, ſmooth Language, or of notional unneceſſary things, which may delight a little, but periſh in the Read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: there is nothing in them, and it is all blown away <hi>as Chaff:</hi> But more eſpecially are we to take heed of the <hi>Leaven of the Phariſees</hi> (which they mingle amongſt, and thereby corrupt the Bread of Life) <hi>viz.</hi> their ſeveral kind of Gloſſes, Diſtinctions, and their own Inventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, meer human Expoſitions and Traditions. Many ignorant People give more regard to the Opinions and Sayings of ſuch a <hi>Rabbi</hi> or Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher, than to what <hi>Chriſt,</hi> the <hi>Prophets</hi> and <hi>Apoſtles</hi> ſpeak, or even what God himſelf ſpeaketh by them. Indeed there was at firſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed a Peculiar, and diſtinct Office of Men to <hi>turn his People away from Iniquity,</hi> Mal. 2. 6. and to <hi>turn them to Righteouſneſs,</hi> Dan. 12. 3. But inſtead thereof, <hi>They ſtrengthen the Hands of Evil-doers, that None doth return from his Wickedneſs,</hi> Jer. 23. 14. And either conceal, or flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter them in Unrighteouſneſs; and ſooth them up in the committing of thoſe things, of which God hath ſaid, <hi>The Soul that ſinneth, it ſhall dye,</hi> Ezek. 18. 4. They are rather <hi>Men-pleaſers</hi> (and yet that is a ſad way of pleaſing men, to lead them blindly on to eternal Miſery) then the <hi>Servants of Chriſt;</hi> for as he taxed the <hi>Phariſees</hi> of old time, ſo do theſe now <hi>reject the Commandment of God,</hi> that they may keep in favour with the chief Princes of this Nation. <hi>For</hi> Moſes <hi>ſaid, Honour</hi> 
               <note place="margin">M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rke 7. 10, 11, 12, 13.</note> 
               <hi>thy Father and thy Mother; and whoſoever curſeth Father or Mother, let him dye the Death.</hi> But ye will excuſe, and vindicate, and juſtifie, if the Children ſhall not only take away the Right and Inheritance of the Father, but after they have taken Poſſeſſion, they proceed to Kill and Murder; as carrying on unjuſt Wars, is intentional Murder all along. <hi>And this is that they may be profitted,</hi> though the outward pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence is for the <hi>Proteſtant Religion</hi> againſt <hi>Popery;</hi> Whereas if it were really ſo, yet if ye had a right knowledge of the Glory and Work of the Lord; The One is not to be advanced, nor the other carried on by ſinful means. It is a wrong and contrary Method, <hi>to build up</hi> Zion <hi>with Blood, and</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>with Iniquity,</hi> Micah 3. 10. But our Prieſts and Prophets do not exhort them to do Right and Equity to their Father, <hi>Making the Word of God of none effect through your own Expoſitions, which ye have delivered; and many ſuch like things doye.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>God is my Witneſs, whom I ſerve in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Goſpel of his Son, and as I hope for any Mercy at his Hand, I do here declare, That what I have already, and do now here<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, is alſo out of a greater Zeal and Emulation for the Truth and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>xcellency of the pure Reformed Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>; which at this day <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> under much Scandal and Reproach by
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:35589:13"/> falſification of an Oath and manifeſt Unrighteouſneſs. This Zeal of mine is <hi>according to Knowledge,</hi> and the certain direction of God's written Word, both of the Old and New Teſtament. For we are not to <hi>uſe Oppreſſion, nor exerciſe Robbery, nor oppreſs the Stranger wrongfully,</hi> Ezek. 22. 29. See the next Verſe, <hi>I will be a ſwift Witneſs againſt the Strangers, and againſt thoſe that Oppreſs the Fatherleſs, and that turn aſide the Stranger from his Right,</hi> Mal. 3. 5. We ought to give no oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion that the Way of Truth be evil ſpoken of: We are to have our Converſation honeſt amongſt the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> and to walk as the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God without rebuke. <hi>Recompence to no man Evil for Evil: Be not overcome of Evil, but overcome Evil with Good,</hi> Rom. 12. 17. 21. as ſuch is the deſign of the <hi>Law</hi> and the <hi>Prophets, Chriſt</hi> and his <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles.</hi> If our Ways and our Doings are contrary, <hi>God ſees it, and it diſpleaſed him that there was no judgment,</hi> Iſa. 59. 15. And ſome one or more ſhould appear forth publickly to teſtifie againſt this National Sin and Corruption. What I have done herein, was to clear a great point, which is to manifeſt the <hi>Moſt perfect Holineſs and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightneſs of God,</hi> who doth not allow to <hi>do Evil that Good may come.</hi> As God is Righteous in all his Ways, and Holy in all his Works; ſo according to his certain promiſe, <hi>Judgment ſhall return unto Righteouſneſs, and all the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pright in Heart ſhall follow it,</hi> Pſal. 94. 15.</p>
            <p>So that it is not a matter of Indifferency what any one thinks, or ſpeaks, or doth herein; but we are to ſide with the <hi>King Immortal, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſible and only Wiſe God</hi> againſt this Tranſitory World, the Folly, Falſhood and Corruption which are ſeen therein. We ought to ſearch and enquire diligently what is written, and to ſpeak and do as We that ſhall be judged by the Law of God in Scripture. Not giving ſo much heed to them, whom the Word ſaith, and Experience confirmeth, <hi>But ye are d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>parted out of the way; ye have cauſed many to ſtumble at the Law; ye have corrupted the Covenant of</hi> Levi, <hi>ſaith the Lords of Hoſts,</hi> Mal. 2. 8. whoſe aſſertion may ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>er be believed than their own Vindication. They may be more properly ſtiled followers of <hi>Mahomet,</hi> than of <hi>Moſes</hi> or <hi>Chriſt,</hi> for theſe were <hi>faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful in all their Houſe;</hi> But they, according to the Impoſtors Doctrine will call ſuch a thing an eſpecial Providence, and Immediate Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance ſent by God, though the means (by which it came to paſs) are againſt his expreſs Word and written Revelation. But what, if ſome that handle the Law, know not God? ſhall this diminiſh from the Righteouſneſs of God, or take away from the Purity and Up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightneſs of his Law? <hi>God forbid; yea, let God be true, and every man</hi>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:35589:14"/> 
               <hi>a Lyar, as it is written; That thou mighteſt be juſtified in thy Sayings, and overcome when thou art judged.</hi> We are ſure that all Scripture came by Inſpiration from God, and therefore all is Truth what that ſaith. And whatever the Practices of others are to keep their places, or to <hi>make a gain of Godlineſs,</hi> (ſo called, but rather Hypocriſie) or procure and retain the favour of the great Ones; yet ſuch will be the greateſt loſers in the end: for there is a real Truth and Signification in theſe Words, <hi>Bleſſed are they that keep Judgment, and He that doth Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs at all times,</hi> Pſal. 106. 3. And though at this preſent ſhort time, <hi>There is one event to the Righteous and to the Wicked, to him that ſweareth, or he that feareth an Oath;</hi> Yet it will be certainly better with thoſe who have continued whole and ſtedfaſt in the Covenant of their God, and have preſerved a good Conſcience in all things. So it will be ſeen and experienced, when of this, and every day of our Life, after years of diſcretion, we ſhall be called to Account; which will alſo extend to every <hi>Idle</hi> and <hi>falſe word</hi> that men do now ſpeak. The time, place, circumſtances and aggravations of ſuch wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Sins and deliberate Acts of Diſobedience will be manifeſted, as they were day by day committed. And then it will be no excuſe to have <hi>juſtified the wicked for Reward,</hi> or for faſhion, or becauſe they had the greateſt number of their ſide, or out of any wrong or indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect Principle. They act fooliſhly, and are ignorant, who flouriſh over and vindicate the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>iolent perverting of Judgment and Juſtice in a Province;</hi> for they may now Read and Underſtand, that the <hi>Moſt Higheſt regardeth the Matter, and there is Higher than they,</hi> who will ſet things at right again. That <hi>wo</hi> which is now denounced againſt them who <hi>call Evil good, and Good evil,</hi> ſhall at length terminate in execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and miſery.</p>
            <p>It is a ſad Thing to conſider that any People for profit and advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, for <hi>pride</hi> and <hi>pleaſure,</hi> to get or keep the good will of their ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour fellow Creatures, ſhould whilſt they live do thoſe things, for which after Death they ſhall ſuffer puniſhment: And they ſhould be more careful fearful to humor and comply with a parcel of Dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Men, whose <hi>Gifts periſh with them,</hi> and their Fury vaniſheth into nothing, then they are to pleaſe an Almighty Father and Everliv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God. Do ye think the Scripture ſaith in vain? <hi>Truſt in him at all times, ye People, pour out your Heart before him: God is a Refuge for us; Selah. Surely Men of Low degree are Vanity, and Men of High degree are a Lye: To be laid in the Ballance they are altogether lighter then Vanity. Truſt not in Oppreſſion, and become not vain in Robbery: If Riches increaſe, ſet not your Heart upon them. God hath ſpoken once, twice have I heard this,</hi>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:35589:14"/> 
               <hi>that Power belongeth unto God. Alſo unto thee, O Lord, belongeth Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy; for thou rendreſt to every Man according to his Work,</hi> Pſal. 62. 8, 9, 10, 11.</p>
            <p>God hath wiſely eſtabliſhed things for a Life of Tryal, and an O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience of Faith, and to exerciſe our Truſt on him. He hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven us <hi>the Law and the Teſtimony, and the Light that is in them,</hi> to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern and know Good and Evil, Truth and Falſhood, Right and Wrong, Subſtance and Vanity. And the Salvation which we ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect from our God, ſhould always keep us in that ſtedfaſt purpoſe of mind, as not to commit any deliberate Sin, nor to continue in any known Tranſgreſſion, nor to practice Hypocriſie, nor to leave Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty undone for to accompliſh preſent things. If men did not talk of it as a Word of Courſe, but do really deſire to get to Heaven (as now they ſee the outſide, and they muſt certainly go off from this Earth) then they muſt not do thoſe things that lead a contrary way, as that Word (which reveals the inviſible things within, and the neceſſary means to obtain) doth expreſly declare. It is no jeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing matter, but rather a ſad ſign that the Curſe of God, which is a fore-runner of his puniſhment, is fallen upon people when they <hi>add Iniquity to their Iniquity, and not come into thy Righteouſneſs,</hi> Pſal. 69. 27. For the next thing which ſucceeds, is to be <hi>blott<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d out of the Book of the living, and not be written with the Righteous,</hi> Verſ. 28. and that is ten thouſand times worſe then to loſe their Lives, Liberties and Eſtates.</p>
            <p>And whereas it is further ſurmiſed, our pure Reformed Religion is more dear, and that would be endangered; It is here deliberate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and adviſedly affirmed, <hi>That the Doctrines and Practices of theſe cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt Times are more dangerous and prejudicial to Souls, than all the Errors and Superſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ions of Popery:</hi> for that ſame Word (which inſtructs in the <hi>way of Salvation,</hi> and makes known what is the <hi>pure and undefiled Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion before God)</hi> doth ſpeak much more againſt Perjury, Lying, Unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, Diſobedience to Parents, Revenge, falſe Accuſation, Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie and an <hi>Hypocritical Nation,</hi> and ſuch like, then it doth againſt Idolatry, Superſtition, and falſe Worſhip. But the Will of God is, (which we muſt alſo do, if we would be ſaved) that we abſtain from them all. Thou declareſt upon Oath that the <hi>Pope</hi> cannot depoſe Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical Princes, and that neither he, nor any Perſon whatſoever, hath Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer to abſolve thee of this Oath, or any part thereof; but what if God ſhould judge that Proteſtant Lay-men cannot abſolve ſubjects from their Oath and Allegiance to a Popiſh King? In Truth, neither can one do it, nor yet the other. The ſame God, who commands that we <hi>keep from Idols,</hi> doth likewiſe enjoyn that <hi>we do no wrong,</hi> and that we <hi>abſtain from all appearance of evil.</hi> It is both folly and Wickedneſs to run from one
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:35589:15"/> unlawful extream to another; and God will ſhew and manifeſt that there is no neceſſity to <hi>proceed from evil to evil, and they know not me, ſaith the Lord,</hi> Jer. 9. 3.</p>
            <p>It is impertinent and irk ſome to explain things ſo every particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; but People are dull of apprehenſion: fears and jealouſies are end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs: and more eſpecially a conſciouſneſs of guilt and wrong is not eaſily ſatisfied, for it hopes to have this excuſe for their Sin, a ſurmiſe of Danger, and they venture upon theſe doubtful things to make more ſure againſt it: for ſo they call ſuch things which are as evidently a breach of the Law, as Adultery and Fornication are againſt the ſeventh Commandment, and are more certainly Sins, then Drunkenneſs is one, as themſelves may know, for compare their Actions with the Law, and <hi>their own Thoughts will accuſe them.</hi> When the Soul hath departed from the Law of the moſt High, ſhe ſeeks out for this or that Imagination to pacifie (but it cannot ſatisfie) the grumblings with in at this preſent time; and which ſhe vainly and falſly hopes will ſave harmleſs as to the future. But notwithſtanding all the <hi>Deceiveableneſs of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nrighteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, ſtrong Deluſions,</hi> and human Allegations; Yet Gods Glory is not, nor can be advanced by ſinful means. For, <hi>The juſt Lord is in the midſt of us, he will not do. Iniquity,</hi> Zeph. 3. 5. and we ought to ſuffer himſelf according to his own Gracious Promiſe to <hi>direct our Work (if</hi> we ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely intend it for him, or otherwiſe it is damnable Hypocriſie), <hi>in Truth, Iſa.</hi> 61. 8. If we would indeed <hi>ride Proſperouſly,</hi> It muſt be becauſe of <hi>Truth, and meekreſs and Righteouſneſs.</hi> For whoſoever doth the Work of the Lord, muſt do it only in the Good and right way, which himſelf doth direct all along, and chalk out in his Word. And this doth ſtrictly forbid all manner of Sin and falſhood. <hi>They alſo do no Iniquity, they walk in his wayes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> thy Word is very pure</hi> Pſal. 119. 3. and verſ. 140. <hi>Sanctifie them through thy Truth, thy Word is Truth.</hi> John 17. 17. neither is the leaſt evil to be done for the beſt end. <hi>Will ye ſpeak wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly for God, and talk deceitfully for him?</hi> Job. 13. 7. and to the ſame purpoſe is <hi>Rom.</hi> 3. 7. 8.</p>
            <p>Here I have not ſo much to do with the clamours of the Multitude; but I ought to give an account to the <hi>Saints that are on the Earth,</hi> and the true Servants and Worſhippers of God; who can better under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand and judge of theſe things. But ye know that every Scribe inſtruct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Kingdom of God, if he would be faithful in all his Houſe ought to ſpeak out all that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> is commanded and made known from the whole Scripture according to <hi>Deut.</hi> 18. 8. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 18. 22. <hi>Jer.</hi> 26. 2. <hi>Mat.</hi> 23. 20. and ſo ye ought to receive and give attendance unto all <note place="margin">Deut. 27. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Gods Word, and to diminiſh nothing, nor loſe ought of it. And
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:35589:15"/> then, If ye mark diligently what is here, and all along ſaid, ye will find that I ſpeak not theſe Things as a man, but both <hi>Law and Goſpel ſay the very ſame.</hi> I ſpeak nothing of my ſelf, nor do I uſe meer Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Arguments, but <hi>I make mention of Gods Righteouſneſs, even of thine only,</hi> Pſal. 71. 16. And therefore I do uſe (according to that diſd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l term of Reproach) ſuch a <hi>farrago</hi> of Scriptures, hodge podge, as they are tagged together. If the ſame imputation is endeavoured to be faſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on me, as was on thoſe <hi>Jer.</hi> 20. 7. <hi>Mat.</hi> 27. 63. 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 8. My anſwer is the ſame; for I ſpeak all along out of the Word of Truth, and make uſe of the <hi>Armour of Righteouſneſs on the right Hand, and on the left.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Do not blame me, but let the Prophet <hi>Ezekiel</hi> ariſe forth and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer for himſelf, as one that would bring in Heatheniſm and deſtroy the true Worſhip of God; for what he ſaith ſo emphatical in his ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venteenth Chapter, on behalf of the <hi>King of Babylon,</hi> according to humane apprehenſion, but in Truth he ſpeaks for the <hi>Oath and Covenant of God.</hi> In verſ. 15. the matter of fact is recited particularly (which may in like manner be applyed by one who knows the exact ſeries of the affairs of our Time) and three Queſtions are asked in ſhort, which imply a ſtrong Negative, as it accordingly fell out; ſo that <hi>they did not proſper, nor yet eſcape who did ſuch things, nor were they delivered.</hi> There was ſome mean time between the Prophets ſpeaking this, and it being accompliſhed. Nay, do ye not accuſe him neither, leaſt your Murmur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings are againſt the Spirit of God which ſpake by him: Who for fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Illuſtration and Confirmation of this point doth in ſeveral other places ſpeak expreſly againſt a <hi>falſe Oath:</hi> And there was not to be any breach nor abſolution from it, for outward conveniency or temporal advantage; as in caſe of the <hi>Gibeonites, Jepthas Vow</hi> and what may be gathered from <hi>Judges</hi> 21. 5, 7. concerning the Tribe of <hi>Ephraim.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And then further, let People take heed of provoking God to Anger, by <hi>limiting the Holy One of Iſrael,</hi> as if Deliverance was begun already, and muſt be accompliſhed by ſuch an Inſtrument only; for herein they ſpeak without the Book of the Lord: why, what ſaith that? <hi>Wilt not thou, O God, which hadſt caſt us off? And thou, O God, which didſt not go out with our Armies? Give us help from Trouble, for vain is the help of man.</hi> Pſal. 60. 10, 11. And ſo likewiſe falſe and ſinful is our fear; or if it were true and reaſonable, yet <hi>vain is the Oppoſition of Man.</hi> For if things were done (as they indeed ought) only according to the Principles of Reſtitution and Juſtice, the exact rules of Righteouſneſs and Wiſdom, purely out of Obedience to God and the Word of his Grace, we ſhould be all ſafe under the Divine Providence and Protection; ſo that <hi>we</hi>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:35589:16"/> 
               <hi>may be bold to do Righteous things, and truſt our God with the event of all.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 4. 5.</note> This is better and more ſafe than to venture upon evil and unlawful means, and ſo ſubject themſelves to preſent confuſion and future Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; for if ſuch an one is reſtored to his civil Right, he may ſee the Work of the Lord, how <hi>Judgement is returned to Righteouſneſs;</hi> and hereby he may be brought over to the pure and uncorrupt Religion; to which he may be the ſooner won over by the honeſt dealing of the true and ſincere Members thereof. But if his Heart be to <hi>do Miſchief,</hi> Dan. 11. 27. and to practiſe Revenge and Cruelty, there is a God above, who according to his workings and methods of old may ſuffer his People for a while to be <hi>miniſhed and brought low through Oppreſſion, Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction and Sorrow: He poureth contempt upon Princes, yet ſetteth he the poor on high from affliction,</hi> Pſal. 107. 39, 40, 41. It is ſaid in the plural num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and he may ſo over-rule it by a clear ordaining Providence pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuant to his revealed Word, <hi>The Land ſhall be forſaken of both her Kings,</hi> Iſa. 7. 16. And then alſo will this be found true, <hi>ſo that we our ſelves glory in you in the Churches of God, for your Patience and Faith in all your Perſecutions and Tribulations that ye endure, which is a manifeſt token of the Righteous Judgment of God, that ye may be accounted worthy of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God for which ye alſo ſuffer; ſeeing it is a Righteous thing with God to recompence Tribulation to them that trouble you,</hi> 2. Theſ. 1. 4, 5, 6. ſo that admitting it ſhould be thus, <hi>Here is the Faith and Patience of the Saints,</hi> that they will rather chooſe affliction, than to commit Sin: and will not refrain from doing Righteous Things, though they did know and were aſſured it would bring ſuffering on them; for ſuch indeed, and none elſe will be accounted <hi>Worthy of the Kingdom of God for which they ſuffer.</hi> But if Men will truſt to the methods of their own Wiſdom, till they are run out, and themſelves are confounded and bafled: And will either before or afterwards uſe ſome unlawful Means to preſerve themſelves from, or get out of Perſecution, <hi>God will proceed to do a mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velous Work amongſt this People, even a marvelous Work and a Wonder, that the Wiſdom of theſe wiſe Men ſhall Periſh,</hi> and they ſhall juſtly <hi>ſuffer as Evil-doers.</hi> Then they will wiſh they had done otherwiſe when it is too late; for ſuch Repentance is the ſame with that of <hi>Judas</hi> or <hi>Eſau,</hi> and the damned in Hell; who when they come to be fully ſenſible of what they have loſt, and are to ſuffer; then only they would have done otherwiſe, when before they were proved the ſame thing, but did it not.</p>
            <p>It would be looked upon as vain Arrogancy and Proud Boaſting, if I ſhould repeat at length and apply what is written and afferted thrice, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. 98, 99, 100. Yet it is thankfulneſs to God the given to ſpeak
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:35589:16"/> out and acknowledge the ſame, and alſo it is a benefit and inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 9. 15. 16.</note> to others to aſſign the very reaſon how ſuch an one came to that Wiſdom and Underſtanding. And likewiſe great heed is to be taken all along that this is confined within the bounds of God's Law. I am doubtful whether I ſhall not Tranſgreſs my Commiſſion to inſert one Human ſaying, <hi>Inter detiria ſenum et prejudicia juvenum cadit Reſpublica;</hi> but ſometimes we are allowed to ſpeak the words of Man's Wiſdom <note place="margin">1 Kings 12. 8.</note> and common obſervation. And notwithſtanding the contempt, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice and diſdain, which may ariſe againſt me becauſe of my <hi>Youth,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 17. 28, 29.</note> 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. 12. and ſeeming forwardneſs; I will add this yet further, and do here take Liberty to make a publick and ſolemn Proteſtation, that according to the Grace &amp; Knowledge God ſhall be pleaſed to continue and further endue me withal, <hi>I will as ſoon ſtand in the gap to prevent the coming in and overflowing of Popery, with my Life, Liberty, and younger Brothers Portion; as now I expoſe them all againſt falſhood and unrighteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</hi> If at any time (either now or hereafter) I ſhould recede and draw back from this deliberate Reſolution of mine here made, then let me be made an object of the utmoſt fury of the Multitude. I would under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go all <hi>Ravilliacs</hi> Torments and quietly ſubmit to the moſt cruel and lingring death that ever yet man endured ſince the World began. This is here publiſhed and record<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> to ſtand againſt and be executed upon me, and that it may be done with me according to mine own words.</p>
            <p>I am as it were neceſſitated to uſe this confidence of Boaſting; for it hath been ſurmiſed againſt me as if I <hi>plead for Baal</hi> and his falſe Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippers; that I have diſplayed a banner for Antichriſt in this Kingdom, and that I am a Miniſter of Satan transformed into a Miniſter of Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs: which laſt is more ſuppoſed of me, becauſe I do <hi>diſcover Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity to turn away our Captivity,</hi> Lam. 2. 14. and that other threatning manifeſted under the Goſpel. And alſo in order to <hi>turn away Iniquity from Jacob,</hi> it is neceſſary to lay open the full aggravation and <hi>ſinfulneſs of Sin,</hi> and alſo to cite the Scriptures; but for doing theſe things I am thought to be like him that <hi>accuſes our Brethren before God day and night.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rom. 11. 2. 3.</note> But then this charge muſt alſo fall upon <hi>Elias</hi> and the <hi>Prophets, Chriſt</hi> and the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> and all faithful Teachers down ever ſince, and at this day; for they according to their Duty and Office did the very ſame. We cannot inform God of any thing, nor make the Sins of Men known unto him, nor recorded before him, for he knows much more himſelf. <hi>The Sin of</hi> Judah <hi>is written with a Pen of Iron, and Graven with a point of a Diamond,</hi> though no mortal Man did in the leaſt Speak or Write thereof. But our God commands that they be ſhewed and told there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, in order to which it is neceſſary to do both. We have no way to
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:35589:17"/> convince of <hi>Sin</hi> and <hi>turn unto Righteouſneſs,</hi> but by the Scriptures; And when the Devil quotes them, as we read that once he did, he leaves out the material Words, <hi>To keep thee in all thy Wayes,</hi> which is in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 91. 11. but quite omitted <hi>Mat.</hi> 4. 6. and in <hi>Luke</hi> 4. 10. <hi>to keep thee</hi> is added, but the laſt Words are again omitted. So that the Allega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is the more ſubtle and fallacious. But our Lord did confront Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to Scripture; and let this be ſhewed and done by my Adverſaries, and not think it ſufficient barely to object the ſame againſt me. Let the <hi>Learned,</hi> but <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nſtable</hi> of our days, ſhew where the Scriptures have been any where wreſted; for there have been cited thoſe places which are eaſie to be underſtood, according to the plain and common ſignifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. But when there is a Comment added to hinder from coming in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the way of Righteouſneſs, then this Imputation will truly fall back upon themſelves, as God will judge and determine at laſt; the now they <hi>juſtifie themſelves before Men,</hi> and have the faſhion and mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude on their ſide. If Satan doth once cite Scripture, not in generals, or by halfs, but particularly and fully to turn People from Iniquity unto Righteouſneſs, then <hi>He doth riſe up againſt himſelf, and is divided: He cannot ſtand and hath an end.</hi> And if my ſelf have done that under all (as I can think of) the principal heads of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ood and Evil, as may be ſeen in the <hi>Book of Happineſs,</hi> &amp;c. to which I have prefixed my Name; then it may be judged whether I am a <hi>true Miniſter of Righteouſneſs;</hi> tho' by the Impoſitions and Reſtraints of Men, I am as yet debarred from the publick and outward Adminiſtration of that Office by reaſon of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictory Oaths, and to me doubtful Subſcriptions. And if my ſelf have wrote againſt <hi>Popery</hi> more than my Equals, as may be ſeen in the above<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited Book, page 75, 120, 121, 160, 190, 212, 243, 253, 411, 460, 461, 462, 487, 586, 618, 691, 700. And yet am a <hi>Papiſt,</hi> then alſo <hi>Popery is divided againſt it ſelf, and that hath an end, and cannot ſtand.</hi> I ſhall never be able to do any thing to advance the Cauſe, but ſubject my ſelf to preſent ſhame &amp; eternal confuſion. If I do once ſpeak or act contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictory to mine own printed words in the leaſt conſiderable inſtance, then I am a <hi>Lyar, Deceiver, falſe Prophet, Traytour, heady</hi> and <hi>high-minded;</hi> and then I may be juſtly and ſafely proceeded againſt as ſuch.</p>
            <p>That Book was indeed compiled in the late King's Reign, but came out of the Preſs after his <hi>departure.</hi> And there is one ſingle page there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>hundred ſixty ſecond;</hi> which if he had been put in mind of, and throughly obſerved, <hi>the Truth contained therein would have preſerved him in his Throne to this day,</hi> and the <hi>enemies</hi> of our <hi>reformed Church</hi> had got no advantage over us. And alſo that <hi>Sin, Diſturbance, Confuſion,</hi> the <hi>bloody</hi> &amp; <hi>doubful events of War might have been prevented,</hi> which we have been ſince involved in.</p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:35589:17"/>
            <p> If I have ſpoken the Truth, it ought to be believed and received; if I am all along conſonant and agreeable to my ſelf (which others may examine as ſtrictly as they will) then <hi>it is Truth.</hi> And if my only drift and deſign is to teach tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſors thy wayes, and that Sinners may be converted unto God, then <hi>the Truth of God is come unto you.</hi> Though according to the Divine Method it may ſpring up from an obſcure preſs, and compiler, and remain for ſome time hidden and concealed from the World, for People <hi>are aſhamed of ſuch Words in an adulterous and ſinful Generation;</hi> and they hate the Light, neither come they to the Light leſt their deeds ſhould be reproved. <hi>The Light ſhineth in Darkneſs, and the Darkneſs comprehendeth it not,</hi> John 1. 5. It doth not ſee and perceive, and alſo it is afraid and ſhrinks thereat. And alſo there is the whole Truth ſpoken out without fear and reſpect of Perſons and without favour of and ſiding with any Sect or party; and alſo the time is come when they will not endure ſound Doctrine. for theſe and ſuch like Reaſons only, it hath been univerſally rejected, and not received.</p>
            <p>I have all my Life time kept conſtant Communion with the Church of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, and have daily frequented its publike Worſhip as I have opportunity, and do at leaſt thrice in the Year receive the Holy Sacrament, according to the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed Inſtitution. I have been alſo ſome few times, ſince the Eſtabliſhed Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty at the Congregations of Proteſtant Diſſenters; and herein I do act pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t to that Truth Manifeſted in the fifth Chapter of my afore-cited Book un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the head of <hi>different communions.</hi> But I did never in the leaſt joyn with the Popiſh way of Worſhip, nor did ever ſo much as ſee it; which <hi>I</hi> have had the curioſity only to incline me ſo far; but <hi>I</hi> thought even that to be a ſin and unlawful, becauſe of their Superſtition and Image Worſhip; and therefore <hi>I</hi> did utterly refrain. <hi>I</hi> do deſire and would endeavour after a Greater degree of purity and reformation even in our eſtabliſhed Church; for it ſhould be yet more freed from the Ordinances and Commandments of men. Though <hi>I</hi> do withal conſider that the <hi>Reſtorer of Paths to dwell in,</hi> Iſa. 58. 12. is only to take away that rubbiſh and corruption (which hath ſo long laid in them) that they may be ſmooth, right and plain as they were at firſt, and they are to remain the very ſame, for we are to come up again to the <hi>old Paths, where is the good way,</hi> Jer. 6. 16. The Wall is in no wiſe to be removed, nor yet the Foundations altered, but the <hi>old waſte places are to be builded,</hi> and they are to be <hi>raiſed up,</hi> and the <hi>breach is to be repaired;</hi> and all is to be done in the very ſame place.</p>
            <p>We would not willingly bring a Scandal, or <hi>Odium,</hi> or Diſhonour them in the ſight of their ſeveral Congregations; but yet <hi>the Sons of Levi are to be puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied,</hi> that they may offer unto the Lord an Offering in Righteouſneſs; and that they might be the ſame as in the dayes of Old, and in former Years; when they did Teach <hi>Jacob</hi> thy Judgements, and <hi>Iſrael,</hi> thy Law; and the Lord did accept the work of their Hands. When they did walk before him in Peace and Equity, and did turn many away from Iniquity. And now the fault is only in themſelves, for why ſhould they do thoſe things as to be <hi>contemptible and baſe before the People?</hi>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:35589:18"/> As their office is to admoniſh the People of their Sin and Errour; ſo God in his abundant Care and Proviſion for his Church, hath all along inſtructed and raiſed up others (who were not of the <hi>Levitical Prieſthood)</hi> to do the like unto them alſo.</p>
            <p>It ſeems to be Ignorance or Intereſt that People are ſo over zealous for, and confined within a particular Church, or ſuch a Congregation; whereas we ſhould acknowledge and anſwer to no other Name than that of a <hi>Chriſtian;</hi> not according to the common notions thereof, but as it is written in the Word of God, by living according to all the Rules and directions there. And then we might all agree to the ſame manner, and meet at the ſame place of Worſhip.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A ſummary of the proceeding Diſcourſe.</head>
               <p>Both the ſecret Thought and open accuſation of the World are affixed on Me for Publiſhing ſuch <hi>Words unto them, This man ſeeketh not the welfare of this People but the hurt,</hi> Jer. 38. 4. He that conquers Kingdoms and enlarges Territories, is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted a Great Inſtrument of Mens Happineſs; though it is accompliſhed with the Price of Blood, and by unlawful means, and the utmoſt hereof is a ſhadow only of Good, which juſt paſſeth by and is gone for ever. But they are the only unaccepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Perſons to the World, who inſtruct People how they muſt live and do, <hi>that they may be ſaved;</hi> and lead them into the right way, that they may live as Peacea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly and comfortably here, as can be well deſired in this World; and at laſt be Happy and Bleſſed throughout all eternity. Men need not be in the leaſt ſcrupul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and fearful as to this preſent time; for theſe Words, if underſtood aright, would prevent that further effuſion of Blood in our neighbour Nations. And one Mans Life, if he knew how rightly to eſteem it, is more valuable to himſelf than two Kings and their Kingdoms. They, according as is was long ſince foretold of them, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 8. do turn their Subjects into Servants, and make uſe of the lower ſort of People for their Wars; <hi>but they have not ſo learned of Chriſt;</hi> for of him it is written, <hi>He ſhall ſpare the Poor and needy, and ſhall ſave the Souls of the needy. He ſhall redeem their Soul from Deceit and Violence, and precious ſhall their Blood be in his ſight.</hi> Pſal. 72. 13, 14. The ſame eternal Word and Truth would put a ſtop to the further impoveriſhment which is likely to fall on our own Nation through continued taxes and charge; which would ſome what take off from the <hi>Oppreſſi-of the Poor and the ſighing of the Needy;</hi> for that is drained out which ſhould carry on Trade and Commerce. The Spirit of God doth take notice of ſuch things, as may be ſeen, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 23. 18. And then the Seas might be ſet open again, that People may follow their lawful Merchandize with leſs fear and Danger. And then again, the like Way and Method may be found out <hi>to reſtore unto all Nati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ns <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity, Peace and Concord,</hi> which we pray for as a Bleſſing, ſo we ſhould likewiſe endeavour after out of a mind to the publick good, <hi>That there be no breaking in nor going out: That there be no complaining in our Streets,</hi> Pſal. 144. 14.
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:35589:18"/> Which would be in Deed and in Truth accompliſhed; If, as they do already own and profeſs him, ſo the Kings and Princes, and Lords and Counſellers, and Paſtors and Teachers of all ſorts, <hi>would obey the Lord our God, and do ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to all his Laws and Statutes.</hi> If they do not, their Sin will find them out ſeverally, and as they are joyned together in a community; for the time draws near, when He will fulfil his Word, <hi>for the Nation and Kingdom that will not ſerve thee ſhall Periſh: Yea, thoſe Nations ſhall be utterly waſted.</hi> Iſa. 60. 12.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Lord executeth Righteouſneſs and Judgment for all that are oppreſſed,</hi> Pſal. 103. 6. How is this true? for many are oppreſſed throughout their Life, and dye ſo. But it is to be underſtood from the words following, <hi>He made known his ways un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Moſes,</hi> Verſ. 7. He hath commanded and ſhewed in his Word how it ſhould be done. And if People will not do it freely and willingly, we his Servants have no more to ſay, but we leave it to God himſelf to perform, fulfil and execute his Word. They may believe and tremble that the ſame Almighty God, who ſpake the World into Being, and commanded his Word to a thouſand Generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, will alſo give forth the executive Sentence. <hi>And I will puniſh the World for their evil, and the Wicked for their Iniquity; and I will cauſe the A rogancy of the Prondro ceaſe, and will lay low the Haughtineſs of the Terrible,</hi> Iſa. 13. 11. which laſt hath been already fulfilled in foregoing Generations, and there is a fearful expectation of the other. The like doth haſte to be accompliſhed and determined upon the preſent Generation, unleſs they agree with their Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary quickly whilſt they are now in the way. Conſider of it ſeriouſly; <hi>Had ye ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther die in your Sins, and utterly Periſh in your own corruption, then be told thereof and be put in a way how you may eſcape?</hi> Now it is high time to look about your ſelves, for now ye are nearer to Death and Immortality then ever ye were yet: and ſo ye approach nearer from Day to Day, till one drop away after another into the future ſtate. And then do appear forth the things contained in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture (out of which I have ſpoken all along) and are manifeſted to our ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Spirits, all one as the Things we now here in the Fleſh do ſee handle and converſe withal. God will take care that what he hath ſaid, ſhall come to paſs. And thoſe who are now ſo ſtout and diſdainful to value his Words as an empty ſound, or a dead impertinent letter which may be laid aſide, and not minded, &amp; ſuppoſe there is not much more in it then waſte Paper with ſome impreſſions of Ink: Or if it is <hi>quick and powerful, and ſharper then any two edged Sword;</hi> then out of the Spirit of oppoſition and revenge they may do as <hi>Jehudi</hi> did, Jer. 36. 23. <hi>Cut it with a Pen-Knife or caſt it into the Fire,</hi> or ſome other way embezil and loſe it: ſuch People may at length find and be ſenſible of an hideous lamentation in themſelves, and that it is become a <hi>Savour of Death unto Death:</hi> As the words in a ſtatute Book do now cauſe ſeveral te ſuffer loſs of Liberty, Life or Member, and other wayes of puniſhment: and that aforementioned is as ſilly a device, as for a guilty offender to tear the Record or Statute by which he is to be judged,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:35589:19"/> for this doth only argue a greater contempt and provocation to God, who did ſend forth his Word to bring them to Repentance, that he might <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give Jer.</hi> 36. 3. and Pardon them. And it remains ſtill the ſame in the purpoſe and determination and Book of the Lord: <hi>From Scripture, all that is truly infer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, will be in like manner fulfilled.</hi> Let there go about never ſo many like <hi>Elymas</hi> the Sorcerer to defeat what is here ſaid; or as <hi>Jannes</hi> and <hi>Jambres</hi> of old time: So do too many now <hi>reſiſt the Truth,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 8. or diſregard it, ſtill that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains: And however in the mean while ſtifled or prevaricated; nevertheleſs it will riſe up at the Judgment of the great Day. Whether they will hear or for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear, whether they will read or not, theſe Words are laid before them, that they might have turned from Iniquity unto Righteouſneſs: And not in Hypocriſie or outward ſhew; but in ſincerity and Truth <hi>ſeek their God daily, and delight to know his Wayes.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Compilers Defence for himſelf.</head>
               <p>And now methinks I hear the whiſpering and ſecret Counſel of thoſe, which may ariſe yet higher, and it ſhall be done in a ſolemn Judiciary proceeding, <hi>Away with this turbulent Fellow, it is not fit he ſhould live;</hi> for he doth exceedingly diſquiet this Nation; we will ſend him away before to prove whether the words he hath here laid together, be true; or elſe do it according to the ſubtlety of the old Serpent in the <hi>lu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>king Places of the Villages, and Murder the Innocent in ſecret Places,</hi> or by adminiſtring ſome deadly thing; for this will not make much noiſe, and we ſhall be thus happily rid of one, who doth and will continue to <hi>Torment the Inhabitants of the Earth;</hi> and therefore one way or another, let him be <hi>Slain.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ye may indeed Kill my Body, but ye cannot Kill me;</hi> for there is an <hi>Immortality, Reſurrection of the Dead and eternal Judgment.</hi> If that ſhould be (which God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid, and yet it may be ſuppoſed, for the like hath been fulfilled in our Brethren, who were <hi>Slain for the Word of God, and for the Teſtimony which they held.</hi> Rev. 6. 9.) yet I ſhall ſee again, and meet with my Murderers. But the ſafer way is to forewarn you all of theſe things. <hi>Hear my Voice, O God, in my Prayer; Preſerve my Life from fear of the Enemy: hide me from the ſecret counſel of the Wicked and from the Inſurrection of the Workers of Iniquity. fear was on every ſide, while they took counſel together againſt me, they deviſed to take away my Life.</hi> But yet with all their ſecreſie, violence and conſultations, they cannot do it in that place and after that manner, where God may not ſee it and know it. And the Lord will find it out when he maketh Inquiſition for Blood, this and that man was put to Death after ſuch a manner, by the Hands of ſuch Perſons, and for ſuch a cauſe. God ſends me as a Meſſenger to his Subjects, to acquaint them of their Violation of his Laws, and to teſtifie againſt them, to turn them to God and Righteouſneſs: And <hi>I</hi> put them in mind to live under his Government, and
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:35589:19"/> to obey his Laws for the future: But for doing of this they ſeek to Kill me. <hi>Help me, O Lord my God: O ſave me according to thy Mercy, that they may know that this is thy Hand: That thou Lord haſt done it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If they ſhould ſend me before, there is no calling of me back again, and ſo no Reſtitution; nor yet will the <hi>Crocodiles</hi> Tears afterwards waſh away the guilt of my Blood; The <hi>building the Tombs of the Prophets, and garniſhing the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulchers of the Righteous</hi> will not make an attonement for the Sin of killing them. And moreover, it will be but a very ſmall advantage and ſhort reſpite; for your Spirits alſo in a little time will fly out one after another. And if they are ſo impatient now, that they cannot endure a ſingle <hi>Troubler of Iſrael,</hi> how then will ye endure to meet with the whole <hi>Company of Prophets and Apoſtles,</hi> who were the very ſame to their Age and Country, what <hi>I</hi> am accuſed of now? How will your ſelves look Chriſt in the Face (the great Preacher of Righteouſneſs) if ye ſhould <hi>offend one of thoſe little Ones</hi> that belongs to him? And proceed in the ſame manner as thoſe did, who <hi>Slew him and hanged him on a Tree.</hi> How will ye anſwer it before God the Judge of all? And excuſe your ſelves to the <hi>Spirits of Juſt Men made perfect?</hi> Who then will be without partiality and reſpect of Perſons: Who will not in the leaſt <hi>ſavour of what belongs unto Men,</hi> and alſo have a right knowledge of both ſides; the want whereof doth hinder the Saints on Earth from giving a righteous judgment. But yet further, your own ſelf-conviction, which is now ſtifled, ſhall break forth; And your own thoughts which now a little accuſe you, ſhall appear fully out, and get the Dominion (as before did the <hi>Thoughts of Iniquity)</hi> and ſhall recoil upon your ſelves.</p>
               <p>This know, and be aſſured of in the mean while, that the Perſecuting Spirit is the Work of the <hi>Dragon,</hi> who hath ſo long <hi>made War with them which keep the Commandments of God,</hi> Rev. 12. 17. and Perſecution or Proſecution of his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants (even as its firſt beginning, to the laſt wicked act) doth ariſe and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue from want of the true knowledge of God; as is evident from theſe fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing places of his Word. <hi>For Strangers are riſen up againſt me, and Oppreſſors ſeek after my Soul; They have not ſet God before them,</hi> Pſal. 54. 3. <hi>O God, the Proud are riſen againſt me, and the Aſſemblies of Violent Men have ſought after my Soul, and have not ſet thee before them,</hi> Pſal. 86. 14. <hi>They ſhall not hurt nor deſtroy in all my Holy Mountain.</hi> Why ſo? <hi>For the Earth ſhall be full of the knowledge of the Lord, as the Waters cover the Sea,</hi> Iſa. 11. 9. <hi>They ſhall put you out of the Synagogues; yea, the Time cometh that whoſoever killeth you, will think that he doth God ſervice: And theſe things will they do unto you, becauſe they have not known the Father nor me,</hi> Joh. 16. 2, 3. <hi>Which none of the Princes of this World knew; for had they known it, they would not have crucified the Lord of Glory,</hi> 1 Cor. 2. 8. He prayed for his Murderers, <hi>Father forgive them, for they know not what they do,</hi> Luk. 23. 34. But <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ow men have no ſuch excuſe for their Sin; neither will God hear, nor are we allowed to pray but according to Truth. <hi>Paul</hi> gives the Reaſon-why he who was a Perſecutor <hi>ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained</hi>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:35589:20"/> 
                  <hi>Mercy, Becauſe I did it ignorantly, and in unbelief,</hi> 1 Tim. 1. 13. which im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies the contrary, if it had been knowingly done. And here again, to be <hi>wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly ignorant,</hi> and to <hi>make haſte to ſhed Innocent Blood,</hi> Iſa. 59. 7. becauſe they hope to have this excuſe for their Sin; This is to <hi>ſeekdeep to hide their Counſel from the Lord,</hi> Iſa. 29. 15. <hi>Shall not God ſearch this our? for he knoweth the ſecrets of the Heart,</hi> Pſal. 44. 21. Or whatever pretence or vindication they may have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the world, can they conceal from his Eyes, <hi>before whom all things are naked and opened with whom we have to do,</hi> Heb. 4. 13. and are to be judged by him on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. For it is a ſmall thing, or nothing to be accountable one to another. But it is a further degree of Sin and Iniquity, &amp; will bring on greater Guilt and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation, when People are not only contented not to obey the Laws and Truth of the Moſt high God, but alſo as their Fathers did to the Prophets, <hi>Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute</hi> and <hi>Kill</hi> ſuch who are appointed to make it known: And all thoſe who are even now for <hi>filling up the meaſure of their Fathers:</hi> Have they not ſo much <hi>knowledge</hi> and <hi>reaſon</hi> to reflect for their own ſafety? Do ye not think, it would have been better for them if they had not <hi>touched God's Prophets, and done his Anointed no harm.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>My Authority and Commiſſion for doing theſe things, is (as aforeſaid) from the 23d Chapter of <hi>Matthew,</hi> and Verſ. 34. And alſo what I can make evident from the 14th Chapter of <hi>John,</hi> and 17th Verſe, <hi>Even the Spirit of Truth;</hi> which by ſome is hard to be rightly apprehended, for the ſame Reaſon as <hi>the World cannot receive him, becauſe it ſeeth him not.</hi> But yet they may conceive thus much, What is that common ſence and reaſon which is within themſelves? May it be felt or ſeen? And is it not only to be Underſtood? That Diſcourſe and infer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of one thing from another, is in order to bring out ſomething that is Truth. The pure acts of the mind may give a Light and glimmering to na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural and reaſonable Souls, that there are higher and Spiritual things, which ſhall ſhortly be revealed before us with open Face, as theſe low and Earthly things are, among which we now dwell; I ſpeak unto wiſe Men, Judge ye of what <hi>I</hi> ſay. <hi>The Truth which I ſpeak, that is my Commiſſion.</hi> And though it is not ſeen, yet it may be ſenſibly felt and evidently perceived within your own Conſciences. <hi>I will put my Words in his Mouth.</hi> Deut. 18. 18. <hi>Behold I have put my Words in thy Mouth,</hi> Jer. 1. 9. and ſuch Words only are a good and ſufficient Commiſſion of themſelves.</p>
               <p>God hath been pleaſed to try many of his Servants even unto the Death, to ſee what they will endure for him: and to let the wickedneſs of Men go on, that he may behold what they will do againſt him. For my part I know not what or when is determined with me; but I truſt on that God who gave me and all mankind Life and Breath. Though my Faith may a little doubt, it w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll not altogether fail, if I ſhould be conformed to the Example of <hi>Chriſt</hi> or <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> to whom that particular Phraſe was, <hi>Behold my Servant whom I uphold</hi>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:35589:20"/> Iſa. 42. 1. Yet both of them fell by the Hands of wicked Men. I have had the application of ſome Promiſes, which encouraged me to this great Work; but yet if I ſhould be cut off in the midſt of my dayes, I do believe and am aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured (for I utterly renounce the perſons of Men) that ſeeing the thing is <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment and Peace</hi> which muſt be laid on an Holy, Righteous, True and laſting Foundation to bring in Chriſts Kingdom) and it is to <hi>Order it and to Eſtabliſh it with Judgment and with Juſtice, from henceforth even forever. The Zeal of the Lord of Hoſts will perform this,</hi> Iſa. 9. 7. Now God doth ſend that into the Hearts of his Servants: And it is an active Principle which will ſtill reach forth where it can apprehend any thing more, until it be firmly and throughly Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed, <hi>He ſhall not fail, nor be diſcouraged till he have ſet Judgment in the Earth.</hi> Iſa. 42. 4. That is the thing we go upon only. And here if one ſimple weak and unworthy Inſtrument ſhould be ſtopt and hindred, or ſhut up and kill<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d; I nothing queſtion, but as <hi>the Lord ſpake thus to me with a ſtrong Hand, and inſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ucted me that I ſhould not walk in the way of this People;</hi> ſo likewiſe he will ſtir up the Hearts of more; for one may be an hundred, and to ten may ſucceed a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand, who will in like manner fully accompliſh what is here imperfectly begun, <hi>for I do only ſpeak out the thoughts of thouſands, and what the Conſcience of all</hi> (even mine Enemies being Judges) <hi>doth aſſent unto.</hi> And though others by reaſon of Unbelief and Diſtruſt, fear and the diſtates of fleſhly wiſdom are, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 56. 10. <hi>quiet and ſtill;</hi> ſo that as in the dayes of <hi>Elias,</hi> I do appear <hi>alone,</hi> Rom. 11. 3. and they account me a Fool or a Mad man becauſe <hi>I know whom I have believed;</hi> I can ſtay on my God as to the preſent, and diſcern his Promiſes as to the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. <hi>I will go in the Strength of the Lord God: I will make mention of thy Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, even of thine only,</hi> Pſal. 71. 16. And I do here affirm, that if I were not hindred by the Devil and his viſible Inſtruments, who have already twice <hi>caſt me into Priſon that I might be tryed,</hi> Rev. 2. 10. God knows only what may be done yet further as to mine own Perſon; but I truſt, as he ſits above, and is the <hi>Almighty God, King of all Kings, and Governour of all things, whoſe Power no Creature is able to reſiſt;</hi> So he will over-rule all, and manifeſt that he is ſtronger and will prevail. And then if his Word hath free Utterance and Paſſage, it will do yet more then Armies and Fleets, national Laws and meer humane conſtitutions: For it will <hi>Rebuke the Company of Spear-men, and ſcatter the People that delight in War,</hi> and break their cords and ſnap their bands aſunder. And the ſame Spirit may be again revived, who <hi>through Faith ſubdued Kingdoms, wrought Righteouſneſs, obtained Promiſes, ſtopped the Mouths of Lyons,</hi> Heb. 11. 33. It is obſervoble how the Holy Ghoſt expreſſeth it here, and alſo <hi>Pſal</hi> 15. 2. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 32. 17. <hi>Asts.</hi> 10. 34. by the phraſe of <hi>working Righteouſneſs,</hi> for that implies Labour, difficulty and ſucceſſion of time. It muſt be worked out, and way made, as we uſe to ſay in common ſpeaking.</p>
               <p>And though the Enemy, who <hi>lets,</hi> may here again ſurmiſe, that this is a
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:35589:21"/> troubleſome ſpirit, which muſt be taken off in the beginning and utterly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſhed before it ſpeads too far; for at this rate we ſhall never have any Peace, or Quiet: Yet let them know, that here <hi>the Heathen do rage, and the People imagine a vain thing,</hi> as quite to ſuppreſs it, and <hi>they think falſly that it will put things out of order.</hi> He ſtill and know that there is a God above, who will continue to <hi>ſend out his Light and his Truth,</hi> till it over-ſpreads and prevails over the Face of the whole Earth. And whoever in the mean while ſhall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to quench and ſtifle it, this is direct <hi>walking contrary,</hi> Lev. 26. 21. and <hi>ſtriving with their Maker.</hi> And it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hall be at length upon them <hi>as a conſuming Fire to devour its Adverſaries,</hi> and they ſhall find <hi>it is hard to kick againſt the Pricks:</hi> The more they oppoſe Truth, it will ſtrike deeper, and wound, and lay them in a greater condemnation. All the World muſt be ſubject unto God. If People do not provoke him to Anger, <hi>he will do you no hurt,</hi> Jer. 25. 6. He is not a terrour to ſingle Perſons, Families or Nations, unleſs they do that which is evil, and tranſgreſs his Laws; and then by further Reſtleſneſs and Provocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, they draw a much greater ſeverity of his threatnings and puniſhment on themſelves. Wilt thou not be afraid of the Government of God over the World, as he doth exerciſe the ſame by the <hi>ſtill Voice</hi> of his Word and Spirit? Do that which is good &amp; Righteous, then thou ſhalt have the approbation of our God at the preſent time, to which ſucceeds an eternal reward. All People (High and Low, Rich and Poor, or whoever they be) had better be Obedient and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſive under this Almighty Power, who ſitteth King for ever, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 29. 10. For they might live as contentedly under him as Subjects under the moſt Lawful &amp; Excellent Prince; Children under the moſt loving, juſt &amp; wiſe Father; &amp; Servants under the beſt of Maſters. Whereas it people be never ſo impatient and toſs to &amp; fro, it is to no purpoſe, but to gaul themſelves yet more, <hi>Only have a good mind towards God;</hi> and shew your ſelves accordingly to his Embaſſadors, who come with the <hi>Word of his Truth;</hi> for no other <hi>intent</hi> and <hi>purpoſe,</hi> but that there might be <hi>Glory to God in the higheſt, on Earth Peace, Good-will towards men,</hi> Luk. 2. 14. <hi>Then Judgment ſhall dwell in the Wilderneſs, and Righteouſneſs remain in the fruitful Field. And the work of Righteouſneſs ſhall be Peace, and the effect of Righteouſneſs quietneſs and aſſurence forever. And my People ſhall dwell in a peaceable Habitation, and in ſure Dwellings, and in quiet Reſting Places,</hi> Iſa. 32. 16, 17, 18.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="postscript">
               <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>LEt no Man (either in the Tranſcribing or Reprinting) add unto, nor diminiſh, nor alter any thing in this Teſtimony of Truth, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out my Knowledge or Aſſent.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>R. S.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
